<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="atom.xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://idanariav.com/blog</id>
    <title>Idan Ariav Blog</title>
    <updated>2025-09-16T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://idanariav.com/blog"/>
    <subtitle>Idan Ariav Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://idanariav.com/general/favicon.ico</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Doing Precedes Being]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/doing-before-being</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/doing-before-being"/>
        <updated>2025-09-16T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Who do you truly want to be? Have you ever felt trapped by perfectionism, waiting for the "right moment" to pursue your dreams? Discover how taking action, instead of waiting for destiny to unfold, can redefine your path and identity.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Who do you truly want to be? Have you ever felt trapped by perfectionism, waiting for the "right moment" to pursue your dreams? Discover how taking action, instead of waiting for destiny to unfold, can redefine your path and identity.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Doing Precedes Being (insight).webp" src="https://idanariav.com/assets/images/doing-precedes-being-insight-dd406f881997ebb1ea62818b9203c2c4.webp" width="983" height="884" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="who-do-you-want-to-be">Who Do You want to Be?<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/doing-before-being#who-do-you-want-to-be" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Who Do You want to Be?" title="Direct link to Who Do You want to Be?">​</a></h2>
<p>As kids, we're often asked what we want to be when we grow up.</p>
<p>Our answers range from the trivial to the extraordinary - like a truck driver or an astronaut. Over time, these aspirations usually change based on our hobbies and talents, evolving into roles such as a musician, painter, or soccer player.</p>
<p>Although our answers may shift, we always carry an image of who we want to become in the future. This vision serves as our inspiration, our north star.</p>
<p>For example, in recent years my dream has been to become a creator, sharing my voice with you in hopes of solving a problem or two in your life, helping you smile a bit more, and encouraging you to explore different perspectives.</p>
<p>Before I could embark on this journey, I believed I had to become an exceptional writer. I sought perfection.</p>
<p>So, I waited.</p>
<p>For three years, "become a creator" lingered on my bucket list while I took one writing course after another, read "just one" more book, and sharpened my mind and pen like a warrior preparing for battle.</p>
<p>I could have waited indefinitely.</p>
<p>Fortunately, one day I decided that enough was enough. I rejected perfectionism, and because of that, I can share this moment with you. Otherwise, these words would have remained buried in a digital drawer or never come to fruition.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="chasing-our-destiny">Chasing Our Destiny<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/doing-before-being#chasing-our-destiny" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Chasing Our Destiny" title="Direct link to Chasing Our Destiny">​</a></h2>
<p>Writing the first post was challenging, but it didn't stop there. I immediately questioned whether writing was "in my cards." I thought that if I were meant to be a writer, I would "feel it" in my bones, my unique talent would reveal itself and make my newsletter sensational overnight.</p>
<p>Any result less than perfect would suggest I was pursuing a dead end and should switch to a different dream.</p>
<p>Now I can tell you - the first step is the hardest, but the second is the most crucial.</p>
<p>It's tempting to believe our destiny is prewritten, that somewhere out there lies our purpose, and that we carry a unique talent waiting to be discovered.</p>
<p>Even if that's true we have no way of knowing it. Consider your life right now - your profession, relationships, and environment. Even if looking back it all "makes sense" that you would be in this place, it's nearly impossible to have predicted it in advance.</p>
<p>According to determinism, everything is preordained, just like the movement of stars, gravity, and even baking - everything operates based on universal rules. We are not exceptions, our complexity is "merely" a chemical brain and a physical body governed by the same laws.</p>
<p>Yet, even in a deterministic world where "free will" is an illusion, we must confront the fundamental question of "what do I want to do now?" along with the more complex one of "who do I want to be?"</p>
<p>This is why I appreciate pragmatism, which claims that "what's true is what works, what helps us navigate life, regardless of absolute physical truths." For instance, instead of asking whether God really exists, a pragmatist would ask, "Does believing in God improve my life? Does religious life or community benefit me?"</p>
<p>Similarly, I view destiny not as a deterministic question about whether we can predict human behavior with endless knowledge, but rather as a pragmatic one. Does believing in fate help us live a better life?</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="wait-for-it">Wait for It?<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/doing-before-being#wait-for-it" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Wait for It?" title="Direct link to Wait for It?">​</a></h2>
<p>Fate encourages us to "wait for it," to search for what comes naturally and to give up if we don't see immediate results, as there's no sense in trying.</p>
<p>Being a pragmatist, on the other hand, calls for action. It's through our actions that we become who we wish to be.</p>
<p>Our destiny is created, not discovered. This resonates with Sartre famous quote (that also inspired the title) - "Existence precedes essence", which means that we come into this world without any preordained plan, and that we have to find "the meaning of life" ourselves.</p>
<p>Don't wait until "you are ready" or for a "sign" to present yourself to the world, you will never be fully prepared. Rather, it is through action that you become ready.</p>
<p>Consider the difference between endlessly watching videos on how to play the guitar and actually trying to play it. You can't be a guitarist until you've made the attempt.</p>
<p>Aristotle said that action creates identity, not the other way around - we become builders by building and moral people by performing moral acts: "We are what we repeatedly do. Excellence, then, is not an act but a habit."</p>
<p>The path of action is scary. We face many obstacles, such as:</p>
<ol>
<li>Perfectionism - "If it's not the best, it's not worth it."</li>
<li>Imposter syndrome - "I feel like I'm pretending to know what I'm doing, while others are the true experts."</li>
<li>Procrastination - "I have to research everything before I begin."</li>
</ol>
<p>Despite these rational fears, our response should remain the same: "I will learn on the go, taking the smallest step possible, and then the next one."</p>
<p>Slowly but surely, acting like the person you want to become will transform you into that person.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Doing Precedes Being (insight).webp" src="https://idanariav.com/assets/images/doing-precedes-being-insight-dd406f881997ebb1ea62818b9203c2c4.webp" width="983" height="884" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p><em>.</em></p>]]></content>
        <category label="Personal-Identity" term="Personal-Identity"/>
        <category label="Challenges" term="Challenges"/>
        <category label="Mindset" term="Mindset"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Find Your Frequency]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/find-your-frequency</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/find-your-frequency"/>
        <updated>2025-09-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Are you struggling to find enough hours in the day to chase your dreams? What if the secret lies not in relentless hustle but in harmonizing with life's natural rhythm? Discover how aligning your efforts with reality can transform your mindset and lead to greater fulfillment.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Are you struggling to find enough hours in the day to chase your dreams? What if the secret lies not in relentless hustle but in harmonizing with life's natural rhythm? Discover how aligning your efforts with reality can transform your mindset and lead to greater fulfillment.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Find your frequency (insight).webp" src="https://idanariav.com/assets/images/find-your-frequency-insight-1b0eb04eccd877111cc8a21bd75c6609.webp" width="734" height="403" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>I often wish there were more than 24 hours in a day.</p>
<p>I don't know about you, but I have so much I want to accomplish and so many aspirations that there simply isn't enough time for everything.</p>
<p>I thought it was a matter of having the right system. By being more productive and seeking the latest tips and tricks, I believed I could find enough time to do it all.</p>
<p>I wasn't just wrong, it was destined to fail from the start.</p>
<p>There's a saying: "don't eat with your eyes." When we are led by our desires, we set ourselves up for failure because they disregard our limitations. Our dreams are endless, but our time, resources, and energy are not.</p>
<p>Trying to satisfy an insatiable hunger detaches us from our true nature as finite beings in a chaotic world. We become out of sync with reality, like a child playing their own music while a different song is playing. It "sounds" wrong, it feels wrong.</p>
<p>We unconsciously attempt to bend the world to our will. For example, if I set a goal to run a marathon by next year, I may feel compelled to achieve it at all costs, regardless of how my body feels, whether I have time to work out, or if it's raining outside. "My will is law, and it will be done."</p>
<p>We praise such behavior, viewing these individuals as "go-getters" who embody "grit," the power to overcome and persevere. We internalize the belief that we must manifest the future we desire, that we should "go big or go home." But like someone trying to sail upstream, we must ask ourselves whether we are "fighting" the world for the sake of fighting, as if blood, sweat, and tears are a badge of honor.</p>
<p>Life is hard, but we shouldn't make it harder.</p>
<p>Seneca (of the ancient stoics) wholeheartedly believed that much of the suffering in life is the result of our judgment, rather than the event itself, or "We suffer more often in imagination than in reality". Regardless of how harsh life is, by thinking that only sheer resolve and unstoppable determination can help us overcome it, we add so much to our burden.</p>
<p>I'm not saying we shouldn't have goals or that achieving something worthwhile won't require effort. I'm suggesting we view life as a song with its own rhythm that we should attune to, rather than constantly trying to change the beat. Let me explain.</p>
<p>Life has its own rhythm. For example, if you sell coats, would it be easier to reach your sales quota in winter or summer? Of course, it's winter. However, if we try to meet the same quota year-round, we will have to work twice as hard and likely not reach it at all. What if, instead, we acted more like (reverse) ants, using the higher sales from winter to survive the summer? If we work just a bit harder during winter, we could sell much more than we ever could in summer. It's not that we don't need to make any effort, but it's smarter and more efficient to align our efforts with life's seasons.</p>
<p>While that was a simplified example, it applies to every aspect of our lives. When we rush things, we often do more harm than good, like someone who dates a different person every day in hopes of finding "the one," without giving each relationship time to develop. Or the person who is so determined to advance their career that they abuse and step over everyone they meet, only to discover that reciprocity is what helps you reach (and stay) at the top.</p>
<p>By wanting it all and wanting it fast, we end up with nothing, or as Lao Tzu says regarding his notion o of "no action" (wu wei): "Rushing into action, you fail. Trying to grasp things, you lose them. Forcing a project to completion, you ruin what was almost ripe".</p>
<p>Instead of trying to control the world and bend it to our will, we must listen. We need to feel the "flow" of reality and ourselves as water flowing within it. Water is the most gentle, flexible, and powerful force in nature. It carves mountains and finds its way into the most closed spaces.</p>
<p>We must find the frequency where our actions harmonize with reality, striking at the optimal location for maximum effectiveness and minimal investment of time and effort.</p>
<p>We need to be flexible in mind and action. Doing that won't just make our life easier, it will change them completely - "The greatest discovery of my generation is that a human being can alter his life by altering his attitudes" (William James)</p>
<p>This means we can't give 100% at all times, our energy is limited. Most importantly, we must learn to let go. Some dreams are impossible to achieve, some will take longer than we would like, and some will adapt and change over time and that's okay.</p>
<p>Most songs sound horrible at 3x speed. Slow down, find your rhythm, and let it play.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Find your frequency (insight).webp" src="https://idanariav.com/assets/images/find-your-frequency-insight-1b0eb04eccd877111cc8a21bd75c6609.webp" width="734" height="403" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content>
        <category label="Self-Control" term="Self-Control"/>
        <category label="Environment" term="Environment"/>
        <category label="Stillness" term="Stillness"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[council of selves]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/council-of-selves</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/council-of-selves"/>
        <updated>2025-08-19T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[What if your inner conflicts are the key to discovering your true "selves"? As we navigate choices shaped by time, relationships, and environment, how do we reconcile our many identities? From conflict to harmony - this journey would be difficult, but it's ours to make.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What if your inner conflicts are the key to discovering your true "selves"? As we navigate choices shaped by time, relationships, and environment, how do we reconcile our many identities? From conflict to harmony - this journey would be difficult, but it's ours to make.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="council of selves (Insight).webp" src="https://idanariav.com/assets/images/council-of-selves-insight-7d04dd09e183c2364d4e1be78e074b51.webp" width="834" height="741" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>What do we have in common with Aladdin and Hamilton? We all see ourselves as a "diamond in the rough."</p>
<p>We believe that beneath our rough edges and unresolved issues lies our "true self." Everything that stands in our way of becoming that self is merely impulses or random thoughts, which can be distractions at best or even enemies to suppress, like the craving for sugar when we want to eat healthily. These are our "inner demons" or "animalistic nature," but they are certainly not part of us.</p>
<p>Avoiding these urges is not simple, but it pales in comparison to the meaningful yet paralyzing moments in life when we must decide who we want to be. Which job should I pursue? Where do I want to live? What do I want to do with my life? Each choice feels both right and wrong simultaneously, as we are filled with conflicting voices that seem like a part of "us."</p>
<p>As agonizing as it sounds, I believe these internal conflicts are a feature, not a bug, of being human. Having multiple voices within us makes more sense when we realize we contain multiple identities, each with its own unique quirks and persona (this is only a metaphor, setting schizophrenia aside). "We are condemned to be free," said Sartre. The choice of who we are at any given moment is difficult, yet it is ours to make; no one else can make it for us. This is the price of having a rich (and free) identity.</p>
<p>Making choices would be much easier if we had only one value or identity to live by. However, it would also make life shallow and unbalanced. Consider people who dedicate themselves entirely to a single cause - workaholics and extreme altruists alike quickly experience burnout as they realize the cost of what they have sacrificed, such as relationships, creative pursuits, and leisure.</p>
<p>But where does our multiplicity come from? We can identify three major sources:</p>
<ol>
<li>Time</li>
<li>People</li>
<li>Environment</li>
</ol>
<p>Let's start with time. Although we change over time, we do not completely detach ourselves from our past. Like covering a wall with fresh paint, the old layer still lies beneath. We may still be affected by baggage, past traumas, and scars that continue to hurt. We might find ourselves boxed into a path chosen by our past selves, such as a degree or a marriage. The choice was made long ago, but it still influences the present.</p>
<p>Our future self is equally alive in the present moment. By imagining who we want to become, it is as if we bring them to life just by thinking about them - a kind of self-fulfilling prophecy.</p>
<p>We also act differently depending on who we are with. The "work self" is very different from the "with friends self" (shoutout to all the Severance fans). It’s not just that we act differently; we are different. We perceive the world through different lenses, altering our thoughts, priorities, and behavior. Each person sees different fragments of us, which together form a complex mosaic.</p>
<p>Pause and ask yourself how much of who you are today results from your relationships with others. Whether you have copied their behavior, been shaped by shared experiences, or developed traits to counteract harmful attitudes, we are who we are because of the people we associate with. William James said, "We are like islands in the sea, separate on the surface but connected in the deep."</p>
<p>Aside from astronauts, most of us do not exist in a vacuum. Our environment is as much a part of ourselves as the soil is to a plant. Our surroundings shape us, sending cues that translate into actions, thoughts, and feelings. For example, taking a walk calms us, while a dark, confined space might make us feel tired or fearful. So, which one is our "true self"? Is it the one who thrives outdoors or the one who feels scared?</p>
<p>From our genes to social groups to space-time itself, we are a vast multitude of beings - a beehive of identities working together for a common(-ish) cause. Once we accept that, we can find greater peace with who we are.</p>
<p>Knowing this is only half the battle. Recognizing the different voices as competing identities is helpful, but how do we get them to agree, or at least quiet down?</p>
<p>The first step is to shift from a "one voice above all" mentality, where terms like "self-control" and "grit" dominate the conversation, to a more "democratic" and deliberative approach.</p>
<p>Start listening to those voices. It might help to give them personas; for me, it works best if these personas are fictional. This way, they can represent a single, pure idea without the complexities of using an existing person for your inner dialogue.</p>
<p>Together, I consider what they would have done, what my future self would do, or what my past self would have wanted in that situation. Which of my core values should I prioritize if they don't overlap?</p>
<p>Sometimes, the big decisions in life are too much for one person to handle. Using the perspectives of all our inner voices can provide more information to work with when making a choice. Perhaps our procrastination is not a vice to overcome but rather a sign that we are doing something we dislike. "(He) who looks inside, awakes," said Carl Jung. Through self-reflection, we gain much more than information; we bring harmony to who we are.</p>
<p>Trusting your past self, who made the right decision at the time, or allowing your future self to guide you can help you navigate life more calmly, even amid rough storms, knowing exactly where you want to go and that you don't have to go there alone.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="council of selves (Insight).webp" src="https://idanariav.com/assets/images/council-of-selves-insight-7d04dd09e183c2364d4e1be78e074b51.webp" width="834" height="741" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content>
        <category label="Personal-Identity" term="Personal-Identity"/>
        <category label="Environment" term="Environment"/>
        <category label="Reflection" term="Reflection"/>
        <category label="Communication" term="Communication"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[You are always a work in progress]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/work-in-progress</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/work-in-progress"/>
        <updated>2025-08-05T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Are you truly aware of the depths of your potential for growth? Just as nature constantly evolves, so do we, yet many of us mistakenly believe we've reached our limit. What if I told you that embracing change is the key to unlocking your true self, and that the journey of self-discovery never truly ends?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Are you truly aware of the depths of your potential for growth? Just as nature constantly evolves, so do we, yet many of us mistakenly believe we've reached our limit. What if I told you that embracing change is the key to unlocking your true self, and that the journey of self-discovery never truly ends?</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="You are always a work in progress (insight).webp" src="https://idanariav.com/assets/images/you-are-always-a-work-in-progress-insight-b6d6eb0c34cd550143793cc1c8b88bfc.webp" width="722" height="781" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Caterpillars grow into butterflies, and tadpoles into frogs. We humans also change, though perhaps in more subtle ways.</p>
<p>Compared to other animals, we are born helpless. However, thanks to our ability to learn and grow, we evolve from babies into mature, capable adults. Our development extends beyond the physical; our minds, values, and even our identities can change as well.</p>
<p>At age 20, I believed I had finally discovered who I am. I confidently repeated this belief at 25, again at 30, and I will likely do so again at 35. In hindsight, we can see how much we've changed, yet we often believe that <em>now</em> we have reached the finish line - that "this is it" and that this is who we will be until the day we die.</p>
<p>I'm here to tell you: you are always a work in progress.</p>
<p>Don't assume your current skill level reflects your potential, nor that your current "vices" are a permanent stain on your identity.</p>
<p>While there may be some truth to the idea that we have a "core identity" or "talent" that limits our potential, it is more accurate to say that "the mind makes it real." When we believe we have reached our limits, we become static. By believing we can change, we expand our possibilities.</p>
<p>Kierkegaard said, "Life can only be understood backwards, but it must be lived forwards." Looking back, we can see how far we've come; the pieces of our lives make sense, and we can trace the twisting yet connected path that has led us to who we are today. We must extend that belief into the future as well. We need to overcome the innate feeling that "our identity is fixed" so we can shape our journey of change moving forward. The path we were on hasn't ended; the way ahead is simply hidden from us.</p>
<p>Change is the one true constant of life. As Heraclitus said, "No man ever steps in the same river twice, for it is not the same river, and he's not the same man." Some ancient Greeks, like Heraclitus, believed that human nature mirrors nature itself - the rules of the cosmos govern people as well. Therefore, if nature is in constant flux, then so are we.</p>
<p>The question is not whether we are capable of change, but how we will change. Like revolving gears, some parts of ourselves shift faster - perhaps our professions or interests - while others change more slowly, like our values and core beliefs.</p>
<p>We are always in the process of becoming, changing from the moment we are born until the day we die.</p>
<p>Therefore, life is a journey, not a destination. It is not about reaching a "perfect version of ourselves" - we will never get there. Not because we are incapable of improvement, but because our idea of a "perfect self" evolves with us. It's like trying to reach the end of a rainbow; it keeps slipping away, distancing itself with every step we take.</p>
<p>Nietzsche once wrote, "What is great in man is that he is a bridge and not a goal." We are always in the process of surpassing ourselves, moving from one identity to the next, rather than unveiling a specific version of ourselves. Kierkegaard claimed, "The self is a relation that relates itself to itself." If you need a moment to process that, it's fine. Essentially, it means that our identity resembles the paper art children create of people holding hands. What makes us "us" (the elusive "self" that separates us from others) is that all the identities we adopt and replace throughout the years <em>feel</em> connected to each other, which creates a sense of continuity.</p>
<p>While a final destination is unattainable, we can surpass many milestones along the way. Who we are today is merely an image, a temporary version of ourselves - the best use of our potential <em>so far</em> - but hardly the best we can achieve throughout our lifetimes. Use the words "yet" and "so far" as your guiding principles, such as "I can't do that yet" or "this is the best I've achieved so far."</p>
<p>By embracing the spirit of change and being "a work in progress," we are not bound by our past or by limiting thoughts about ourselves. Our potential is much greater, and our limits extend much farther than we think.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="further-reading">Further Reading<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/work-in-progress#further-reading" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Further Reading" title="Direct link to Further Reading">​</a></h2>]]></content>
        <category label="Change" term="Change"/>
        <category label="Personal-Identity" term="Personal-Identity"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Walking a Tight Rope]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/walking-a-tight-rope</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/walking-a-tight-rope"/>
        <updated>2025-07-08T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Is living a good and happy life truly an impossible balancing act? How do we strive for our values while recognizing our limitations? Explore the delicate dance between self-improvement and self-acceptance, and discover how facing hardships can lead to growth. Are you ready to find your balance amidst life's challenges?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Is living a good and happy life truly an impossible balancing act? How do we strive for our values while recognizing our limitations? Explore the delicate dance between self-improvement and self-acceptance, and discover how facing hardships can lead to growth. Are you ready to find your balance amidst life's challenges?</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Walking a tight rope (synthesis).webp" src="https://idanariav.com/assets/images/walking-a-tight-rope-synthesis-ee78510823798705c9d41143baafb2a2.webp" width="1254" height="818" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>We aspire to be good people, yet it's unrealistic to expect ourselves to be saints who volunteer all day. We aim to achieve great things in life, but this often comes at a high cost, such as neglecting our relationships. We seek a calling, yet we often face either an overwhelming number of options or none at all.</p>
<p>If only life were that simple, but it is quite the opposite. Finding a meaningful goal and committing to it is challenging enough. On top of that, we grapple with competing values that pull us in different directions, making every step forward a struggle.</p>
<p>Despite how difficult it may seem, I believe this complexity is a fundamental aspect of being human. To illustrate this, let's explore alternative ways of living.</p>
<p>Kierkegaard identified two types of unsatisfying lives:</p>
<ol>
<li>Being lost in the finite - dedicating yourself entirely to one project and becoming one with it, spending all your time, thoughts, and focus on it.</li>
<li>Being lost in the infinite - attempting to "do it all," succumbing to FOMO with an endless pursuit of an ever-growing wish list, and feeling a constant need to change your life and try something new.</li>
</ol>
<p>I would add a third option that he overlooked:</p>
<ol start="3">
<li>The concept of "philosophical suicide" as described by Camus - giving up entirely and living without striving for anything "special" in life, feeling that everything is meaningless or arbitrary.</li>
</ol>
<p>I believe we oscillate between these ideas rather than fixating on just one.</p>
<p>We may immerse ourselves in our jobs, working long hours at the expense of friendships and sleep. Once we reach the top, we might feel compelled to compensate for what we missed, attempting to check everything off our bucket list. Yet, along the way, we may experience an indescribable emptiness despite fulfilling many dreams.</p>
<p>We often gravitate toward one of these options because it provides certainty. In our quest for life's meaning, we tend to choose the most convenient option available, regardless of its truth. Living with uncertainty, constantly questioning the big issues without answers, is frustrating, to say the least.</p>
<p>But what is the alternative? To walk a tightrope above the abyss of being human:</p>
<p>• To commit to a cause while remembering that we are not defined by a single aspect of our lives.
• To choose a path, even if it feels arbitrary like many others, knowing we may never see its end.
• To strive for improvement while embracing our imperfect selves.</p>
<p>There is no easy answer to where this balance lies, but it is the only answer we have.</p>
<p>We can debate, argue, and deny, but just as the Earth revolves around the sun despite our beliefs, we cannot escape the abyss.</p>
<p>We can only decide how to cross it.</p>
<p>This is a journey you must undertake on your own. No one can make the choice for you, and be cautious of those who promise you "the truth to a good life."</p>
<p>That answer will likely evolve over time, just as you do, and that's perfectly okay.</p>
<p>This is why my slogan is "join the journey." I don't have all the answers for you, but together, we might find some inspiration.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="ask-yourself">Ask Yourself<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/walking-a-tight-rope#ask-yourself" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Ask Yourself" title="Direct link to Ask Yourself">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li>What does being a "good person" mean to me, and how do I strive to embody that in my daily life?</li>
<li>In what areas of my life do I feel I am sacrificing one value for another? How can I create a better balance?</li>
<li>What are my passions and interests, and how do they align with my current pursuits?</li>
</ol>]]></content>
        <category label="Personal-Identity" term="Personal-Identity"/>
        <category label="Reflection" term="Reflection"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Preparing against Luck]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/prepare-against-luck</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/prepare-against-luck"/>
        <updated>2025-06-25T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Do your decisions set you up for the next move - or just help you survive this one?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Do your decisions set you up for the next move - or just help you survive this one?</strong>
We often rely on mental shortcuts to get through busy days, but what if those shortcuts are quietly keeping us stuck? Learn how thinking beyond the immediate payoff can transform your decision-making and your future.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Preparing against luck (insight).webp" src="https://idanariav.com/assets/images/preparing-against-luck-insight-2964850addf8d709727a5d6bbc3dfc28.webp" width="1728" height="1402" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="making-choices-that-compound">Making Choices that Compound<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/prepare-against-luck#making-choices-that-compound" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Making Choices that Compound" title="Direct link to Making Choices that Compound">​</a></h2>
<p>Decisions are complicated as it is. We are too busy, too tired or so against complexity that we tend to decide based on heuristics.</p>
<p>Heuristics are automated decision rules, like "more is always better" or "free beats quality".</p>
<p>The good thing about heuristics is that in many cases they work just fine, that's how they became automatic. Bad rules that lead to bad outcomes aren't automated, unless...</p>
<p>Unless we're talking about the long term. Heuristics are great for short-term decision-making, but bad for the long term because thinking about the 8th chess move ahead is much harder than thinking about the very next one. Such complexity can't be easily translated into a simple rule, which is why it's often neglected.</p>
<p>For example, the prisoners' dilemma is a problem of heuristics. Each person chooses the betray to maximize their well-being, even though the overall outcome is worse for both sides.</p>
<p>Compare that to a repeating prisoners' dilemma where tit-for-tat (aka kindness) is the winning strategy.</p>
<p>The bigger the decision, the more we must abandon our heuristics, and think about positioning.</p>
<p>Positioning means looking beyond the current decision into the next one. It's asking ourselves what is becoming harder/impossible to do and vice versa. Which choices help me become better positioned for the future.</p>
<p>Classic cases of improving our positioning are physical fitness, being financially responsible, avoiding addictions or distractions, and learning and growing.</p>
<p>Preparing for the future might be hard and not rewarding at first, but it makes our lives so much easier. Instead of running from crisis to crisis, being forced to make bad decisions, and feeling stuck, we are always moving up.</p>
<p>Like leveling up in DND, we improve with time, ready to handle the scary monsters life is going to throw at us.</p>
<p>However, positioning isn't free. Choosing to learn a new course over resting to be "better prepared for the future job market", taking more stuff with you on camping "just in case", or investing less so you can have emergency money are all costly decisions.</p>
<p>Time is scarce, and each decision comes at the cost of not doing something else. So balance between improving your positioning and the alternative cost of what you're missing out.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="ask-yourself">Ask Yourself<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/prepare-against-luck#ask-yourself" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Ask Yourself" title="Direct link to Ask Yourself">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>What decisions am I making today that can limit or expand my future options?</li>
<li>Which habits or actions position me for better choices later?</li>
<li>Am I optimizing for now or setting myself up for the future I want?</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-bottom-line">The Bottom line<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/prepare-against-luck#the-bottom-line" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Bottom line" title="Direct link to The Bottom line">​</a></h2>
<p>Some decisions are important and impactful enough that we should consider their long-term effect. By doing so, we can choose the path that improves our positioning, making future problems easier or nonexistent.</p>
<p>Instead of running from crisis to crisis, we can be on the path that avoids them entirely.</p>
<p>Archimedes said: “Give me a lever long enough, and a place to stand, and I will move the earth.</p>
<p>Positioning, while not free, is a great multiplier that makes good decisions less costly and much more impactful.</p>]]></content>
        <category label="Perspective" term="Perspective"/>
        <category label="Self-Control" term="Self-Control"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rigid Vs Flexible Rules]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/rigid-vs-flexible-rules</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/rigid-vs-flexible-rules"/>
        <updated>2025-06-12T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Is it better to live by rigid rules that offer clarity—or flexible ones that offer resilience?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Is it better to live by rigid rules that offer clarity—or flexible ones that offer resilience?</strong>
What if the very thing that makes strict principles powerful is also what makes them brittle? Explore how we can stay true to our values without breaking under the weight of perfection.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="rigid_vs_flexible_rules.webp" src="https://idanariav.com/assets/images/rigid_vs_flexible_rules-461bce82d71a31408f7f1ca466ce0da0.webp" width="552" height="744" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="too-rigid-or-not-too-rigid-that-is-the-question">Too Rigid, or not Too Rigid, that is the Question<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/rigid-vs-flexible-rules#too-rigid-or-not-too-rigid-that-is-the-question" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Too Rigid, or not Too Rigid, that is the Question" title="Direct link to Too Rigid, or not Too Rigid, that is the Question">​</a></h2>
<p>As a secular person, the thing that I love about religion is also the thing that frustrates me.</p>
<p>No, this is not a post about religion, but it will serve a point.</p>
<p>You can't help but be in awe by the way religious people can maintain a certain way of life as if there wasn't even an option to choose any other way. They live consistently by their moral code, which is more than most of us can say.</p>
<p>There's power in having creeds. When we have an unbreakable rule, such as "I don't eat meat", it makes life easier because we don't have to debate each time whether we should eat meat or not. The expectations are clear.</p>
<p>Also, we can't make excuses - like "nuggets are not really meat because it's chicken". There's no one else to fool but ourselves.</p>
<p>Such rules are likely to become our second nature. With time, discipline turns to automatic behavior, becoming our default.</p>
<p>However, every rule is bound to be broken, whether by mistake, bad luck, laziness, or enough pressure, we will slip up.</p>
<p>When rigid rules are broken, they are broken "big time". These rules are so entrenched in our identity, that when they break - we break. Our motivation collapses, and there's no going back now.</p>
<p>Like a person with 2000 days streak on Duolingo that skipped a single day (without streak freezes), they'll likely delete the app and stop learning for months if not ever.</p>
<p>If you don't want to put all your eggs in the "rigid rule" basket, you can choose to have flexible rules, like "I try to avoid eating meat". It doesn't mean you never eat meat, and (unfortunately) it's up to you to decide what counts as following this rule.</p>
<p>On the bright side, failing to uphold this rule is not as shattering as breaking a rigid rule. Even if you fail by your standards, you can get back up. The fall isn't that high.</p>
<p>You can reflect on your choices, what led to your failure, and what can you do better next time. You can also improve your standards with time. At first "avoid eating meat" can be translated as eating meat every other day, and with time it can be "only on special occasions".</p>
<p>Flexible rules acknowledge our humanity, the good and the bad.</p>
<p>Yes, we can lie to ourselves and make excuses, but it also allows us to adjust based on our circumstances, and to get back up after we fall. The important thing is to focus on being true to values essence, and not to a perfect unreachable version of them.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="actionable-tips-how-to-set-smarter-compassionate-rules">Actionable Tips: How to Set Smarter, Compassionate Rules<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/rigid-vs-flexible-rules#actionable-tips-how-to-set-smarter-compassionate-rules" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Actionable Tips: How to Set Smarter, Compassionate Rules" title="Direct link to Actionable Tips: How to Set Smarter, Compassionate Rules">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Stay true to values, not rules</strong> – Being a moral person is more complex than following rigid rules, we are humans, we slip up, we have multiple conflicting values, and we live in complex reality. So focus on being true to your values, good behavior will follow</li>
<li><strong>Build flexibility in</strong> – Allow yourself some "mulligans", like streak freezes for cases when following the rule simply isn't possible. Give yourself a chance to skip without calling it (and yourself) a failure.</li>
<li><strong>Celebrate resilience, not just consistency</strong> – Be compassionate to yourself, remember that getting back up is more important than staying on track.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="ask-yourself">Ask Yourself<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/rigid-vs-flexible-rules#ask-yourself" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Ask Yourself" title="Direct link to Ask Yourself">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Do I tend to lean toward rigid or flexible rules in my life?</li>
<li>Have I ever lost motivation after “breaking” a rule?</li>
<li>How can I build rules that honor both values and self-compassion?</li>
</ul>]]></content>
        <category label="Habits" term="Habits"/>
        <category label="Self-Control" term="Self-Control"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[dont hate what is good]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/dont-hate-the-good</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/dont-hate-the-good"/>
        <updated>2025-05-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[What if the things that frustrate you are actually signs of trust, love, or care?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>What if the things that frustrate you are actually signs of trust, love, or care?</strong><br>
<!-- -->Could it be that some conflicts come not from bad intentions, but from misreading what “good” looks like to someone else?</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="dont-hate-the-player-dont-hate-the-game">Don't hate the player, don't hate the game<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/dont-hate-the-good#dont-hate-the-player-dont-hate-the-game" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Don't hate the player, don't hate the game" title="Direct link to Don't hate the player, don't hate the game">​</a></h2>
<p>I’m sure you’re wondering about this post’s title. Who would hate good things? Sounds obvious that we would enjoy or at most ignore them, but hate them?</p>
<p>Let’s explain with a story. You’re at work, your projects are piling up along with the stress, and you do what you can to not fall behind, and suddenly your coworker comes to you <em>again</em> with questions that they should have known by now. It has become a routine, they come to you with questions, so much so that you can’t barely keep up with your own work. Frustrating, right?</p>
<p>Maybe you had a tough day and all you want to do is to have a date night with your partner, but when they come home they say a quick “hello” and start doing house chores. You wait for them to talk to you but they’re just so focused on other things that you feel ignored.</p>
<p>The more obvious, common-place takeaway from these stories is that we need to communicate better, and have clearer boundaries and expectations. However, there’s a different message I would like to discuss.</p>
<p>The problem starts with how we judge these interactions. Even if they don’t go as you want them to, that doesn’t mean they’re inherently “bad”</p>
<p>It is shocking how many conflicts are caused because people have different perceptions of what is considered “good” or a desired outcome.</p>
<p>We are so entrenched in how we see the world, and how the interaction affects us, that we fail to see the values and motives behind the other’s actions.</p>
<p>“Nagging” Colleagues trust you, they value you as their mentor, and they acknowledge your expertise. Perhaps they are frustrated that it’s a one-way connection, that they can’t help you the way that you help them.</p>
<p>Your partner probably tried to take care of things so that you could relax. They have expressed their care using their love language, which might be different than your own.</p>
<p>Would you have liked to be someone who is ignored or whose opinions teammates undervalue? Would you want your partner to be self-centered, rather than expressing their love the way they know how?</p>
<p>Even if the method or the final result is not optimal, usually the interactions in our close relationships are based on care, respect, and empathy.</p>
<p>Saying it, and feeling it are two different things.</p>
<p>Our default is to judge the situation from our perspective, it’s crazy to think that we can be a perfect stoic, an unbiased observer at all times. By default, we will get angry, frustrated, or disappointed.</p>
<p>The question is what do we do the moment after we feel these feelings.</p>
<p>I can’t stop myself from feeling it, but I can choose how to act on it. On my better days, I stop and ask myself “Did they try to do good?”</p>
<p>Almost always the answer is yes, but simply asking myself that question calms me down. It allows me ever so slightly to get out of my head, and have a glimpse of how they see the world.</p>
<p>Instead of my “good” and their “good”, we can create together “our good”, a basis for shared understanding and cooperation.</p>
<p>So don’t hate the good, see what lies behind it, and heck, you might even like it.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="ask-yourself">Ask yourself<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/dont-hate-the-good#ask-yourself" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Ask yourself" title="Direct link to Ask yourself">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li>Have you had times where you tried to do good, but received frustration in return?</li>
<li>When was the last time I got mad? What has caused it?</li>
<li>What were the intentions behind the other person's actions?</li>
<li>Could there be a more optimistic/altruistic reason for it?</li>
<li>How could you better communicate your reasons to others?</li>
</ol>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/dont-hate-the-good#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2>
<p>We have a tendency to become frustrated, angry, or resent things that are actually good in our lives. Embracing, rather than denying the good in our lives is a matter of perspective, yet as is with any case of anger and frustration, we first have to stop, calm down, and reflect until we can see the positive side.</p>]]></content>
        <category label="Communication" term="Communication"/>
        <category label="Perspective" term="Perspective"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Are We Capable of Change]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/are-we-capable-of-change</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/are-we-capable-of-change"/>
        <updated>2025-05-13T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[What if real change isn’t about improving who you are, but becoming someone new entirely?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>What if real change isn’t about improving who you are, but becoming someone new entirely?</strong><br>
<!-- -->We often try to change habits or traits, only to feel stuck, like something deeper is holding us back. Could that something be our identity? And if so, what happens when we try to change it? This post explores why lasting personal growth requires more than surface tweaks, and what it really takes to transform.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="are_we_capable_of_change.webp" src="https://idanariav.com/assets/images/are_we_capable_of_change-2ba189a18bb25214534f4a92a3b1c9c9.webp" width="553" height="511" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="introduction">Introduction<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/are-we-capable-of-change#introduction" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Introduction" title="Direct link to Introduction">​</a></h2>
<p>Chances are, there are aspects of yourself that you wish to change. Even if we love ourselves (as we should), we often desire to be a bit better - more loving, outgoing, productive, less lazy, or less prone to Distractions. We all have something we'd like to improve, yet we often doubt whether real change is possible.</p>
<p>How can we truly become someone different from who we are? When we attempt to change, it sometimes feels like there's a force holding us back, an anchor that keeps us in place. Perhaps this anchor is our "true identity," making any meaningful change seem like a distant dream. We may believe that while small changes are possible, the significant ones are out of reach. But is this really true?</p>
<p>We often imagine change as a simple matter of swapping out traits, habits, or thoughts, as if we were replacing components on a list. However, this is more like playing a game of Jenga - remove or change too much, and the whole structure risks collapsing.</p>
<p>This collapse is the harsh reality of change: it’s not easy, but it is a fundamental part of the process. Changing something significant about ourselves inevitably involves altering our identity. Once we accept that meaningful change requires us to adopt a new identity, we must also come to terms with letting go of the old one.</p>
<p>In essence, we can change, but in doing so, we transform who we are. It's almost like saying the same person doesn’t change; rather, they are replaced by a slightly different version of themselves. Over time, these small shifts accumulate, resulting in a drastically different personality. This may sound extreme, but think about how different you were as a child. How much of who you are today can be traced back to who you were then? Some core tendencies might remain, perhaps a similar sense of humor, but your thoughts, values, and preferences have likely evolved dramatically. While you share the same body (more or less), you are hardly the same person anymore, and that's a good thing.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-potential-for-radical-transformation">The Potential for Radical Transformation<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/are-we-capable-of-change#the-potential-for-radical-transformation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Potential for Radical Transformation" title="Direct link to The Potential for Radical Transformation">​</a></h2>
<p>We need to reconcile two seemingly conflicting truths about our identity. On one hand, we feel a strong sense of continuity in "who we are." As we grow older, certain core aspects like being an introvert, our political ideologies, or our automatic reactions to specific triggers seem fixed and unchanging. However, scientific evidence increasingly shows that change is indeed possible. Perhaps more surprisingly, our actions shape our identity as much as our identity shapes our actions.</p>
<p>Who we are and what we do are deeply interconnected, influencing each other in a continuous feedback loop.</p>
<p>This process is known as Habituation, driven by our brain's preference for energy efficiency. Our brains work to simplify decision-making by turning complex, mentally taxing choices into automatic habits. This self-reinforcing loop causes us to repeat certain behaviors without conscious thought. For example, brushing your teeth in the morning, checking your phone multiple times a day, or craving popcorn at the movies are all habits formed through repetition. While this tendency can be limiting, it is also liberating. Whatever change you seek to make may be challenging initially, but it will become easier as new habits form.</p>
<p>If you start eating healthier, over time, you'll find yourself craving salads as you once craved junk food. Acting kindly towards others makes us more compassionate, and practicing gratitude makes us more optimistic. Aristotle’s assertion that by practicing virtue we become virtuous has finally been validated after 2,000 years. Change is a matter of building momentum; it’s difficult to start, but once it gets rolling, it becomes unstoppable. Just like pushing a boulder over a hill, the initial push requires the most effort.</p>
<p>By adulthood, we're no longer "tabula rasa," or blank slates, easily shaped and influenced. We accumulate habits, both good and bad, which become deeply ingrained. Because these habits are easy to perform, replacing them becomes a real challenge. This is why changing ingrained habits is like developing muscles, it requires a strong, decisive effort.</p>
<p>You can't "gently" abandon old habits; it takes a firm commitment to break away from them. If you have even a little willpower, now is the time to use it.</p>
<p>That said, change isn't about relying on willpower alone. Since habits form from repeated decisions, the key is to create an Environment where the "old you" finds it hard to thrive, and the "new you" finds it easier to emerge. For example, if you want to eat healthier, remove unhealthy snacks from your house and stock up on nutritious options. Smart change is not about facing temptation but about eliminating it. If your phone distracts you, "dumb" it down; if you lack empathy, challenge yourself to say three kind things to someone each day.</p>
<p>It will be painful and difficult at first, but the essential takeaway is that change is possible. Studies show that people aged 20 to 80 reported significant personal change over the past decade but anticipated little change in the next. We mistakenly believe our current selves are our final versions, but nothing could be further from the truth. New experiences lead to new habits, which in turn lead to new identities.</p>
<p>With each action we take, we move closer to our ideal selves. Who we are now is just a starting point, and who we wish to become is the goal. Our focus should be on charting the path from here to there, deciding what’s worth keeping and, more importantly, what’s worth discarding, and doing so with all the courage and resilience we have.</p>
<p>You can drastically change who you are because you already have. You are not the same person you were at 5, 10, or 15 years old, so why should now be any different?</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="challenges-of-transformation">Challenges of Transformation<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/are-we-capable-of-change#challenges-of-transformation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Challenges of Transformation" title="Direct link to Challenges of Transformation">​</a></h2>
<p>How do we know if a change is truly beneficial? How can we be sure our desire to change comes from a genuine aspiration to improve rather than from a misguided direction? And if change is so valuable and positive, why is it often so difficult? Perhaps our natural resistance to change is not a flaw, but a feature.</p>
<p>No matter your perspective on change, it is undoubtedly intimidating, especially when we recognize how drastic and even disruptive it can be. Changing our identity is like moving a plant to a new climate; if we don't make the process gentle, the plant might not survive.</p>
<p>At first glance, it may seem contradictory to discuss change as both drastic and gentle. The distinction lies in the difference between form vs essence. The method of change, the form, must be decisive and powerful enough to uproot old habits and replace them with new ones. Trying to gently transition while still holding onto the past will likely fail, much like keeping temptations readily available in a rehab clinic.</p>
<p>To make change stick, we must show determination, resilience, and unwavering connection to our motivation, acting as if any other life is neither possible nor desirable.</p>
<p>However, the essence of change, what we aim to become, should be a manageable shift from who we are now. Radical transformations, like going from a couch potato to a gym enthusiast overnight, or from a quiet introvert to a social butterfly, are unrealistic. Too much change at once can overwhelm us, leading to a backlash against the idea of change altogether. Humans can only handle so much transformation at a time; pushing beyond that limit risks triggering resistance, pain, or fear that can halt progress. The key is to recognize a continuity between who we are now and who we wish to become. The future version of ourselves must feel familiar enough that we don’t feel like we are losing our identity entirely.</p>
<p>When the change is too drastic, uncertainty grows exponentially, and this threatens us at our core. Uncertainty about who we will become, whether we will still enjoy the same things, or what our lives will look like generates existential fear, similar to the fear of death, because it feels like the end of our current identity. We experience this dread during pivotal moments in life, such as finishing school, getting married, or becoming parents.</p>
<p>By focusing on small, manageable changes, we can reduce this fear. We allow a connection to form between who we are now and who we want to be. It becomes, "I'm still me, but a little healthier," or "still me, but a bit more outgoing." This approach maintains continuity between our different selves, like a council of evolving identities.</p>
<p>The magic happens when we realize how a series of small, manageable steps can lead to significant transformations over time.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="embracing-the-process-of-self-transformation">Embracing the Process of Self-Transformation<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/are-we-capable-of-change#embracing-the-process-of-self-transformation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Embracing the Process of Self-Transformation" title="Direct link to Embracing the Process of Self-Transformation">​</a></h2>
<p>In the TV show <em>Fullmetal Alchemist</em>, magicians can create extraordinary things, such as turning water into wine, using three fundamental principles:</p>
<ol>
<li>The ability to destroy, tearing apart what they touch.</li>
<li>The ability to reconstruct, using available resources to create something new.</li>
<li>The energy and extra materials needed to fuel the conversion.</li>
</ol>
<p>Every meaningful change follows these three steps. First, we need the power to deconstruct. This means clearing space for who we want to become by breaking down habits and mindsets that hold us back. Next, we must have the ability to reconstruct. It’s not enough to simply eliminate the old; we need to fill that newly created space with something new and better. Without this, we risk falling back into old patterns or being overwhelmed by a sense of emptiness. Finally, we need the energy to fuel this transformation—the willpower and desire to stop the cycle of current behaviors and bring forth a new identity.</p>
<p>This process of transformation is not a one-time act; it’s a lifelong journey. As long as we are alive, we have the potential to perform incredible feats of personal growth. By embracing this cycle of creative destruction and reconstruction, we open ourselves to becoming so much more. No change or identity is beyond our reach, as long as we understand that it requires time, effort, and vision. Our identity is not a fixed point but a dot on a spectrum of possibilities—each version of ourselves slightly different from the last, yet all connected by a shared vision and history.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="conclusion-the-journey-of-radical-change">Conclusion: The Journey of Radical Change<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/are-we-capable-of-change#conclusion-the-journey-of-radical-change" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion: The Journey of Radical Change" title="Direct link to Conclusion: The Journey of Radical Change">​</a></h2>
<p>Change is often seen as something beyond our control, whether dictated by fate, biology, or the environment. While these forces may shape us, they don't have to hold us back. The reach of our potential is often limited only by the strength of our will. Many of us worry more about these perceived boundaries than we do about actually challenging them. If we commit to change with time, effort, and focus, we can dramatically transform ourselves, enriching our identity with growth and depth. Change is a journey—are you ready to take the first step?</p>
<p>The boundaries of our personal development are shaped by the limits of our will, mind, and body. Interestingly, the more we understand these limits, the more we can push them. As we embark on this journey of growth, every step we take—especially when guided by thoughtful planning and deep reflection—helps us redefine who we are, what we value, and what our purpose is. This continuous self-discovery leads us deeper into understanding and expanding our potential.</p>
<p>Change is the only constant in life. Our experiences and circumstances constantly evolve, challenging our identity and pushing us to adapt. Resisting this natural flow can lead to feelings of stress, frustration, and even victimhood. Conversely, accepting that change is inevitable allows us to flow with it, not against it. embracing this truth is not only more realistic but also more liberating. It enables us to grow into a more resilient and adaptable version of ourselves.</p>
<p>The first step toward meaningful change is acknowledging that change is not only possible but unavoidable. Instead of ignoring, resisting, or fearing change, we should focus on asking ourselves how we can grow for the better. What actions can we take today to move closer to the person we want to become? By embracing this mindset, we realize that our limits are farther away than we once believed. Circumstances do not dictate destiny, and while change is hard, it is never impossible. By adopting a "yes and" attitude, we can better navigate the flow of life and actively choose the direction we want to follow.</p>
<p>When we view change as a choice rather than a mere occurrence, it becomes a profound exercise of our freedom. This freedom is not only about deciding what to do but also about choosing who we want to be. Although challenging, this journey is one of the most empowering, authentic, and liberating paths we can take.</p>
<p>So, what journey are you planning to embark on? What changes have always been on your bucket list but felt out of reach? What steps will you take today and tomorrow? Let these questions inspire you to take action and embrace the possibility of transformation.</p>
<h1>## Further Reading</h1>
<p>master of change (book)
How to change (book)
Switch (book)</p>]]></content>
        <category label="Change" term="Change"/>
        <category label="Personal-Identity" term="Personal-Identity"/>
        <category label="Habits" term="Habits"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Self Love and Change]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/love-and-change</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/love-and-change"/>
        <updated>2025-04-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[How can you truly change if change means rejecting who you are?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>How can you truly change if change means rejecting who you are?</strong><br>
<!-- -->It seems paradoxical: if self-love means accepting yourself, how can it also fuel transformation? But the truth is, change rooted in self-hatred leads to burnout and hopelessness, while change fueled by self-love becomes an act of nurturing growth, not denying who you are. This post explores why real transformation starts not with rejection, but with care.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="self_love_and_change_post.webp" src="https://idanariav.com/assets/images/self_love_and_change_post-625e8d0cb2857e71359624fbf86a2296.webp" width="829" height="312" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>They say that you can't change without loving yourself first, but that seems paradoxical.</p>
<p>Change by definition means out with the old and in with the new, it's a rejection of what exists to make room for the "better" version, so how could self-love even make sense?</p>
<p>If we love ourselves too much, won't we want to stay exactly as we are?</p>
<p>For years I thought that I needed to be ruthless towards myself, that by being my worst critic I would overcome the fear and laziness of change.</p>
<p>Like a drill sergeant I will erase the parts of myself that I don't like, and work effortlessly to develop the good parts. I would break me down to build myself back up again.</p>
<p>The "pain" of being hard towards myself seemed like the price I have to pay, similar to physical workouts where "no pain no gain".</p>
<p>It took me a while to see how harmful that perception was.</p>
<p>Imagine yourself as a captain of a ship. The ship is not great, you've seen better. The color fades in places, some parts are rusty, and it is far from the dream boat that could take you where you want to go.</p>
<p>What would happen if you hate that ship for all that it's not? For all it's flaws and imperfections? Hate won't magically turn it into your dream boat, on the contrary, you would either harm it yourself, or simply neglect it. Without proper maintenance and care, the ship would worsen even faster.</p>
<p>Alternatively, if you loved the ship despite it's flaws, you would take good care of it. You would replace the broken parts, paint it every once in a while, and even invest time and money into improving it. It might never become your dream boat, but it will be the best boat you can have.</p>
<p>Yes, the metaphor was a bit "on the nose", but you get the picture. You can't grow into something beautiful out of self-hatred. Hatred is a vicious mindset, if we hate who we are now we would find things to hate even if/when we become better people.</p>
<p>Even if we could push ourselves hard enough until good habits are the default, we would be miserable, feeling like slaves to ourselves, never good enough, never deserving love or appreciation.</p>
<p>But can we even change with that mindset? When we hate ourselves, what's the point of getting better? Hatred and belittling go hand in hand. We probably believe deep inside that at best we can only do marginal changes, or hide our bad qualities but never get rid of them.</p>
<p>It is a self-fulfilling prophecy of steady unhappiness, like being Sisyphus driving that rock up a hill.</p>
<p>Loving ourselves is not narcissism. It is believing in our potential. Becoming a better person requires work from the "lesser" version of ourselves. Doing that work isn't easy so if we managed to change, it is only because we already possessed the qualities needed to do so.</p>
<p>To love ourselves means to be our own gardener, to enjoy seeing ourselves blossom. .</p>
<p>To love ourselves means to love all the different parts of ourselves, the good and the bad, and all the versions of ourselves, past and future.</p>
<p>While it is never easy being human, to balance between doing and being "more", with the satisfaction of who we are and what we have now, I hope that you have time to stop and appreciate yourself.</p>
<p>Self compassion will lessen the paradox, by increasing the satisfaction from who you are, while also giving you the strength to become better.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="further-reading">Further Reading<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/love-and-change#further-reading" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Further Reading" title="Direct link to Further Reading">​</a></h2>
<p>Master of Change (book)
The Happiness Advantage (book)</p>]]></content>
        <category label="Change" term="Change"/>
        <category label="Kindness" term="Kindness"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Joy of Doing Nothing]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/happy-doing-nothing</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/happy-doing-nothing"/>
        <updated>2025-04-15T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[What if doing nothing is the most productive thing you can do?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>What if doing nothing is the most productive thing you can do?</strong><br>
<!-- -->In a world where time always feels scarce, we squeeze every moment for output, often at the cost of our creativity and peace of mind. But what if the key to clarity and original thinking lies in stillness? This post explores how “do nothing” meditation can restore your focus, spark creativity, and give you back a sense of spaciousness in your day.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="joy_of_doing_nothing.webp" src="https://idanariav.com/assets/images/joy_of_doing_nothing-640a216ec6596f4f6a462bd8ef9ca707.webp" width="1044" height="552" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Doing nothing is apparently very hard.</p>
<p>It sounds ridiculous, right? Usually something is hard because it's exhausting, because it demands our full attention and energy. Doing nothing sounds like the opposite of that.</p>
<p>But even for just five minutes, all I could think of was what I could have done with that time. I could read, I could do chores, I could start an episode, or go to bed sooner.</p>
<p>As if five minutes were the "make or break" of my day, stopping the productivity train seemed wasteful and illogical.</p>
<p>I (and probably most of you), have an urge to do something, to treat time as a resource that must be spend wisely, because how can we not? It's not like we're immortal, and it's not like life is too easy that we can just lay back and rest.</p>
<p>Even when we are not productive, like doom scrolling or watching tv, we feel guilty, so we can't shake that urge or sense of obligation to utilize our time well. That guilt weighs on us like Sisophysus's boulder until we're crushed by it, going to sleep exhausted so we can repeat the process tomorrow.</p>
<p>Another difficulty was to quite my mind. I tried focusing on my breath, on my body, visualizing my thoughts pass by like clouds in the sky, nothing worked.</p>
<p>Even Meditation was something I tried "doing right", to think of nothing, to focus on my breathing or body.</p>
<p>I realized that what bothered me, aside from having a mind that refuses to shut up, is that this kind of meditation, with it's countless rules on how you should do it well, was draining rather than renewing my energy.</p>
<p>Paradoxically, I replaced productivity guilt with meditation guilt.</p>
<p>However, there's a good ending to the story. After a year of experimentation, I finally found the meditation (if we can call it that) that works for me - a do nothing meditation.</p>
<p>As the name suggest, I don't "try" to do anything, which includes trying to quite my mind or maintaining a posture.</p>
<p>Meditation shouldn't feel forced or exhausting. The only rule is that I can't physically do stuff, like working or doing chores, but other than that anything goes. It's okay to think, it's okay to lose focus, it's okay if I move a bit, it's okay to just "be" or let my mind wander.</p>
<p>And apparently, doing nothing for five minutes feels like forever in a good way.</p>
<p>The stress that clouded my mind evaporates, bringing clarity and calmness.</p>
<p>I get the most creative thoughts precisely because I don't try to suppress my mind, I let it run free without interruptions, without being stuck in the feeling that I "have to do something", whether being productive or trying to control my attention.</p>
<p>I get off the "hustle train" for five minutes a day, and yet it's the most productive and rejuvenating part of my day.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="ask-yourself">Ask Yourself<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/happy-doing-nothing#ask-yourself" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Ask Yourself" title="Direct link to Ask Yourself">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li>When was the last time I felt truly refreshed? What was I doing?</li>
<li>Do I have opportunities to relax during the day?</li>
<li>How do I feel about doing literally nothing?</li>
<li>What would happen if you take a whole day off for yourself?</li>
</ol>]]></content>
        <category label="Stillness" term="Stillness"/>
        <category label="Creativity" term="Creativity"/>
        <category label="Recharge" term="Recharge"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Morality is like Colors]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/morality-is-like-colors</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/morality-is-like-colors"/>
        <updated>2025-03-31T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Is morality as different as it seems, or are we all mixing the same basic ingredients?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Is morality as different as it seems, or are we all mixing the same basic ingredients?</strong><br>
<!-- -->Just like all colors stem from a few primary shades, our wildly different moral beliefs might be built from a shared set of core values. This post explores the idea of “moral primary colors” and how understanding them could help bridge the gap between divided perspectives.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="morality_like_colors.webp" src="https://idanariav.com/assets/images/morality_like_colors-e7c8867027f89333ae0d3435f7e4ac79.webp" width="810" height="780" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="introduction">Introduction<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/morality-is-like-colors#introduction" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Introduction" title="Direct link to Introduction">​</a></h2>
<p>When we look around we see an almost infinite range of colors, each seemingly standing on its own without any apparent connection to the others. However, we know that every color is just a different combination of a few "basic colors," like red, green, and blue.</p>
<p>Morality is quite similar in this sense. We observe a vast diversity of moral views, whether between societies or within them, there often seems to be a gap so wide that it’s easy to think there is no common thread in morality at all - that it is entirely relative or perhaps even non-existent. Sure, different groups may agree on certain issues, but that often seems more like a strategic compromise than genuine moral alignment.</p>
<p>However, I believe that there are "basic colors" of morality. abstract notions of virtues and values shared by all humans, just combined differently in each case. Similar to how every color can be represented by a combination of the same three primary colors, moral values can also be seen as combinations of foundational elements.</p>
<p>Knowing how and why we are different won't cause us to magically agree with one another, but it would make understanding easier, and this is a good important step.</p>
<p>Here, we will explore what these "basic moral colors" might look like, where they come from, and what we can do to bridge the gaps between us.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-big-bang-of-moral-views">The Big Bang of Moral Views<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/morality-is-like-colors#the-big-bang-of-moral-views" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Big Bang of Moral Views" title="Direct link to The Big Bang of Moral Views">​</a></h2>
<p>It's almost redundant to say that we often don't agree with each other. Disagreement is simply everywhere, just turn on the news, attend a protest, or have dinner with your extended family. This divide seems deeply rooted, we don't just disagree about a specific political candidate or policy, it’s the underlying values these things represent that seem so obvious to us. We often think, "How could they not see it?" or "If I just explain it to them, they will surely agree with me."</p>
<p>However, they usually don’t. It feels like they see the world through a completely different lens. To us, it seems like a distorted one, to them, we are the blind ones. Wherever you look, there's a vast spectrum of beliefs. It's actually surprising that humanity has made it this far and that we have relatively "few" violent conflicts nowadays.</p>
<p>Without delving too much into the details, this explosion of diverse moral views began in the last few centuries after the decline of "super ideologies" that had dictated our way of life and thoughts, such as religion and nationalism. "God is dead and we have killed him", said Nietzsche, and the question that follows is, "What comes next?"</p>
<p>With the rise of Individualism, Post-Modernism, and identity politics, we now see a broader range of moral views, partly because they are no longer censored or silenced. People are free to express themselves, and some might feel a need to stand out by developing a slightly different variation of their environment's moral beliefs.</p>
<p>As a result, instead of a few ideologies that are imposed upon us (forcefully or subconsciously), we now have a vast spectrum of views on topics like gender, climate change, immigration, and economics.</p>
<p>However, it isn’t entirely random. This is precisely why we have managed to survive (so far) without a complete societal collapse. We can see correlations between certain views that group us into ideological camps, like liberals and conservatives. Yes, there are many differences within these groups just as there are between them, but they still share some similarities.</p>
<p>I argue that these groups form because they are situated near each other on several moral scales, similar to a monochromatic spectrum where all possible outcomes are combinations of the same fundamental colors.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="our-shared-moral-scales">Our Shared Moral Scales<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/morality-is-like-colors#our-shared-moral-scales" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Our Shared Moral Scales" title="Direct link to Our Shared Moral Scales">​</a></h2>
<p>What are these "moral colors"? Below are eight scales that represent my interpretation of moral disagreements. Of course, these could vary, you might see six, ten, or different variations of them. But as long as we can agree that some scales exist, we can begin moving in the right direction.</p>
<p>It’s worth noting that a person doesn’t have to occupy the same position on the scale for every topic. On some issues, they may lean toward one extreme, while on others, they may be closer to the opposite end. Also, it's unlikely to find someone purely on one end of a spectrum. Since these scales represent values that we all care about, some compromise is expected.</p>
<p>Additionally, these scales are relevant both at the individual and societal levels. As nations often reflect the image of their populations, it is no surprise that moral deliberation on the individual level applies to countries as well.</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Sanctity vs. Exploration</strong> - This scale reflects how fixed or flexible we consider our values.</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Sanctity</em>: Some values are held as sacred, unquestionable truths that must be preserved. Sanctity isn't necessarily religious; for example, those who advocate for animal rights may see their suffering as an unquestionable moral concern.</li>
<li><em>Exploration</em>: Truth is both "out there" and continuously evolving. To align with it, we must keep exploring, questioning, and adapting our beliefs, holding few or no values as absolute in an ongoing effort to stay aligned with "humanity's evolving spirit." For example, slavery turned from common practice to taboo because we adjusted our beliefs.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Equality vs. Merit</strong> - This scale focuses on the issue of rights and entitlement.</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Equality</em>: Rights are inherent to every person by virtue of existence, without any other conditions or justifications. Being human, or a conscious being, is enough to have a moral worth, and these rights should be equal for everyone, regardless of any other criteria.</li>
<li><em>Merit</em>: People should be judged by their merits, which may mean a different distribution of rights and resources. For instance, individuals might be entitled to the fruits of their labor and creativity, provided everyone has an equal opportunity to demonstrate their worth. It's not who we are, but what we do that determines our value.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Individuality vs. Community</strong> - This scale addresses who is considered the "smallest" morally relevant unit and whose well-being is prioritized.</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Individuality</em>: The individual is the primary or sole source of value. They are the judge, jury, and executioner of their path to fulfilling their potential. Societal rights are only granted as long as they serve personal interests, and the ultimate goal of society is to make the individual as free as possible.</li>
<li><em>Community</em>: The community is the main source of value. Humans, as social animals, are subcomponents of the community. Individual rights are granted by the community as long as they serve the greater good, and the ultimate goal is the welfare of the community itself.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Security vs. Connectivity</strong> - How much risk are we willing to take for potential benefits?</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Security</em>: The primary goal of society is to maintain the safety of its members above all else, treating others with suspicion and building "walls" (both literal and metaphorical) to separate ourselves from them.</li>
<li><em>Connectivity</em>: Strength and vulnerability are intertwined and gained by being connected to others. This perspective emphasizes forming complex networks of dependence and cooperation.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Destiny vs. Cultivation</strong> - This scale deals with the extent of control we have over our abilities and lives.</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Destiny</em>: Many aspects of life are beyond our control, even our beliefs, skills and thoughts are mainly predetermined either from birth or culture. We should acknowledge that and learn to work within our boundaries, to not "fight our nature", so that we could avoid disappointment, frustration and failure.</li>
<li><em>Cultivation</em>: Our true potential is not only unknown but also within our power to shape and increase. We are the makers of ourselves, of our identity and our destiny.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Permissiveness vs. Dedication</strong> - what is the importance of values and living virtuously?</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Permissiveness</em>: Life is about being in the moment and seeking experiences that bring joy and happiness to oneself and perhaps others. We forgive our weaknesses, understanding that to be human is more than living a perfectly virtuous life. It is not just impossible, it's highly depressing.</li>
<li><em>Dedication</em>: We either find or create our purpose in life, a calling that drives us and demands our time, effort, and thought - even at the expense of personal happiness. Abandoning this mission would mean failing ourselves and what we stand for.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Redemption vs. Retribution</strong> - How should we respond to those who harm us?</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Redemption</em>: "Evil" may not exist or often stems from ignorance, negligence, circumstances, or miscommunication. In these cases, it's not a moral problem, but rather a technical problem that can be solved. Improving the system, like education and welfare can reduce "evil", and most conflicts can be settled through discussion.</li>
<li><em>Retribution</em>: True and lasting peace is achieved only when "evil doers" are deterred by punishment. Evil must be confronted and eradicated, otherwise, unchecked selfish tendencies will lead to corruption, embezzlement, and reduced cooperation and trust.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Authority vs. Diversity</strong> - Should there be a hierarchy governing interactions between people?</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Authority</em>: Stability and prosperity are achieved when all parts know their place and work together seamlessly, following rules and guidelines that provide clarity and deter deviations.</li>
<li><em>Diversity</em>: Rules and guidelines are often at odds with the complexity of human experience. Strength and creativity come from a non-hierarchical structure built on a diverse network of voices that share ideas and collaborate without external supervision. The network self-regulates without a clear "ruler."</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="how-to-bridge-the-gap">How to Bridge the Gap<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/morality-is-like-colors#how-to-bridge-the-gap" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to How to Bridge the Gap" title="Direct link to How to Bridge the Gap">​</a></h2>
<p>Hopefully, regardless of your political views, you found yourself resonating, at least partially, with both sides of each scale described earlier.</p>
<p>If so, then we are already a step closer to bridging the gap between different viewpoints. Recognizing that both sides of a debate have worthy values means that it's all about prioritizing values, rather than claming that some values are "wrong". Once we understand that, we find more common ground with those on the "other side." It’s not that they believe in something entirely different or that they "don’t see the truth"; rather, they assign different weights to the same values and choose to prioritize one over the other.</p>
<p>This is what it means to hold values in a world with limited time, resources, and capabilities. Consider the choice between helping the poor and improving healthcare. Ideally, we would do both and wish for everyone to be better off, but real life often forces us to make tough choices.</p>
<p>It's in these moments, when we must prioritize one value over another, that we truly actualize our values. It’s not about blindly sticking to a value but rather assessing its relevance and importance in each decision and weighing it accordingly. The same value doesn't have to always take precedence. Sometimes equality matters more, and other times, merit does.</p>
<p>Understanding this doesn’t solve all the world’s conflicts. Disagreements will continue to arise, but if we can at least stop demonizing the "other side," we can come closer to understanding and compromising. After all, we aren't made of different things, just different combinations of the same foundational elements, and that’s something we can work with.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="conclusions">Conclusions<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/morality-is-like-colors#conclusions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusions" title="Direct link to Conclusions">​</a></h2>
<p>What might seem like completely different worldviews are, at their core, simply different prioritizations of the same fundamental values. Each value is "paired" with another, creating a dynamic where, in this world of scarcity, we are often forced to compromise between them. However, regardless of where we find ourselves on these moral scales, we can recognize that those we disagree with also care about the same values we do, they just prioritize them differently.</p>
<p>Understanding this shifts the perspective from seeing others as "demons" with opposing values to viewing them as neighbors with different value weights. While this realization won't solve all of our conflicts, it does bring us one step closer to finding common ground and engaging in meaningful deliberation rather than confrontation.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="further-reading">Further Reading<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/morality-is-like-colors#further-reading" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Further Reading" title="Direct link to Further Reading">​</a></h2>
<p>The Righteous Mind (book)</p>]]></content>
        <category label="Ethics" term="Ethics"/>
        <category label="Communication" term="Communication"/>
        <category label="Perspective" term="Perspective"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[From Enemies to Allies]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/enemies-into-allies</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/enemies-into-allies"/>
        <updated>2025-03-18T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[What if the person on the other side isn’t the problem at all?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>What if the person on the other side isn’t the problem at all?</strong><br>
<!-- -->Conflicts are inevitable, but how we handle them makes all the difference. Instead of assuming bad intent, what if we saw the behavior or situation as the issue, not the person? This post explores how shifting our mindset can turn confrontation into collaboration.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="from_enemies_to_allies.webp" src="https://idanariav.com/assets/images/from_enemies_to_allies-0068614e4ae8ef0962a1ab1978863f13.webp" width="566" height="434" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="how-not-to-handle-a-conflict">How (not) to Handle a Conflict<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/enemies-into-allies#how-not-to-handle-a-conflict" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to How (not) to Handle a Conflict" title="Direct link to How (not) to Handle a Conflict">​</a></h2>
<p>We want our relationships to be smooth, pleasurable experiences.</p>
<p>We hope that each will reach a level of synergy and understanding that goes beyond words.</p>
<p>Yet, as with all relationships, conflicts will happen. Your boss is angry about missing a deadline, your kid doesn't listen to you (for the thousandth time), your friends say something hurtful, and your partner doesn't do their share of the chores.</p>
<p>Conflicts are unavoidable, the question is how to approach them.</p>
<p>The unfortunate default response is to be filled with anger, disappointment and resentment. We feel as if we "can't help it", as if it's our body's automated response. Through red colored glasses, we see the conflict through the "blame game" eyes.</p>
<p>We say things like "why did you do this to me?", "why do you always do x on purpose?", "how can you be so inconsiderate?".</p>
<p>When we are on the yelled side, we get defensive, we shift the blame back to the other person, we rebel against their wishes, we yell, we quit, we hide, whatever's necessary to protect ourselves. After all, how can we accept being treated that way? Once the fight begins, it's no longer admitting to making a mistake, rather that we are a bad or stupid person (or both).</p>
<p>The blame game only ends in one way, the worst way. It turns disagreement into conflict, it escalates, it hurts, and it fails to solve the problem that caused it.</p>
<p>We need to handle conflicts better, or more correctly, not treat them as conflict in the first place.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="from-conflict-to-cooperation">From Conflict to Cooperation<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/enemies-into-allies#from-conflict-to-cooperation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to From Conflict to Cooperation" title="Direct link to From Conflict to Cooperation">​</a></h2>
<p>A disagreement becomes a conflict once we see the other person as the problem, instead of the problem as the problem. If our kids doesn't listen to us, it's because they are lazy, inconsiderate, or selfish.</p>
<p>We attach the problem to their identity, which means the only way the problem will be solved is if they change who they are.</p>
<p>Instead, we should see the problem as the problem. What caused the event? Why is there a miscommunication? Perhaps they don't understand what you're asking, perhaps they want to do it yet fail because of distractions or forgetfulness, perhaps they were having a really bad day so your request should be the last thing on their mind.</p>
<p>Remember that most likely, people are not "out to get you", they hardly do things intentionally to hurt you, even if it seems that way.</p>
<p>When we shift the perspective from "they are the problem", to "there's a problem", a whole new range of options opens up that gives a much healthier view on the situation.</p>
<p>When the other person is not the problem, you turn them from an enemy to an ally.</p>
<p>Allies can use their collective intelligence, motivation and energy to solve a shared problem. Being enemies usually only make the problem worse. It's a huge difference when the "other side" works with you, not against you, offering solutions that you might not have thought about.</p>
<p>For example, a criticizing boss doesn't mean they are a disagreeable person, rather it's a shared communication problem. Having a sync at the start of a project instead of at the end will make sure the plan works for both sides, preventing the criticism in advance, without targeting someone as problematic</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="actionable-tips-how-to-turn-conflict-into-collaboration">Actionable Tips: How to Turn Conflict Into Collaboration<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/enemies-into-allies#actionable-tips-how-to-turn-conflict-into-collaboration" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Actionable Tips: How to Turn Conflict Into Collaboration" title="Direct link to Actionable Tips: How to Turn Conflict Into Collaboration">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Pause before reacting</strong> – Take a breath before assuming the worst.</li>
<li><strong>Describe the problem</strong> – Instead of blaming, describe the problem objectively, as something you both face together.</li>
<li><strong>Use “I” statements</strong> – Say how the situation affects you rather than accusing. Like "I feel that..." instead of "you always..."</li>
<li><strong>Seek their input</strong> – Ask them how they view the situation, and which solutions they can offer.</li>
<li><strong>Look for common ground</strong> – Focus on shared interests, not differences.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="ask-yourself">Ask Yourself<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/enemies-into-allies#ask-yourself" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Ask Yourself" title="Direct link to Ask Yourself">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>How do I typically react to conflict?</li>
<li>Have I ever assumed bad intent when there was none?</li>
<li>How can I better separate the person from their behavior?</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/enemies-into-allies#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2>
<p>A disagreement is nothing more than a shared problem, one that we can work together to solve. Turning it into a blame game makes it a conflict, where both sides get hurts and the problem remains unsolved. Remember - the problem is the problem, not the person.</p>]]></content>
        <category label="Communication" term="Communication"/>
        <category label="Cooperation" term="Cooperation"/>
        <category label="Mindset" term="Mindset"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I'm (still) an Optimist]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/why-im-an-optimist</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/why-im-an-optimist"/>
        <updated>2025-03-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Is optimism naive, or a powerful way to shape reality?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Is optimism naive, or a powerful way to shape reality?</strong><br>
<!-- -->With so much going wrong in the world, pessimism feels like the “realistic” choice. But what if the way we see the world changes what we get from it? This post explores how choosing optimism isn’t about ignoring problems—but believing we can overcome them.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="why_im_still_an_optimist.webp" src="https://idanariav.com/assets/images/why_im_still_an_optimist-a268ae0fff035ba491dc150b7713ac92.webp" width="1263" height="980" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="introduction">Introduction<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/why-im-an-optimist#introduction" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Introduction" title="Direct link to Introduction">​</a></h2>
<p>Is the glass half full or half empty? Are people inherently good? What will become of our world? Given the wars, epidemics, and political turmoil in recent years, it's hard not to lean toward pessimism. In fact, it might even seem realistic to believe that things will probably go wrong.</p>
<p>However, what we see is what we get. When we choose to view the world through dark-colored glasses, it's no surprise that everything suddenly seems more depressing. While we don’t control the world, we do control how we view it, and this choice has a significant impact on how we experience life, others, and our overall well-being.</p>
<p>Becoming an optimist can strengthen our relationships with others, improve our happiness, sharpen our minds, and help us solve problems rather than drowning in them. Don’t get me wrong - optimism isn’t about ignoring our problems. It’s about having the conviction that we can overcome them and knowing that even when new problems arise (and they will), they won’t stop us from becoming who we can be and believing that we can make things better.</p>
<p>So, let's happily dive in.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="optimism-to-the-rescue">Optimism to the Rescue<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/why-im-an-optimist#optimism-to-the-rescue" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Optimism to the Rescue" title="Direct link to Optimism to the Rescue">​</a></h2>
<p>While we can relate the optimist/pessimist dilemma to how we view the world, the most important question is how we view <em>our</em> world - what happens to us personally (who wouldn't agree that we matter most?).</p>
<p>More specifically, the question is how we perceive supposedly negative things that happen to us and the challenges we face. We often revert to becoming the victim, thinking, "Why did this happen to me?" or "How will I ever overcome this?" We feel powerless, hopeless, and angry at the world, as if a huge rock hangs above our heads or walls surround us, threatening to crush us. Worst of all, even if there are some good things that come along with it, we become completely blind to them or dismiss them because they clash with our "victim narrative."</p>
<p>The biggest, hardest, and most meaningful change we can make is to realize that events are neither good nor bad - we make them so. This doesn't mean we are indifferent to them; we would never be indifferent between losing a loved one and winning the lottery. Nor does it mean we won't experience negative emotions like anger or sadness. Unpleasant things will happen, and pain will come, but what we choose to do about it is entirely within our control.</p>
<p>When we understand that our reaction is completely in our hands, that we are always free to choose how to respond, we realize the power we have over any situation. We can transform obstacles into stepping stones, using these obstacles as opportunities to grow, learn, and become better.</p>
<p>Those who choose to drown in misery are consumed by it and become slaves to it. Their mental and physical health weakens, they remain stagnant, and they focus on failure, unable to see a way out. However, when we choose to see the usefulness in these obstacles, when we see a chance to rise above them, we are most likely able to. It's fake it till you make it all the way to the top. We acknowledge that having challenges is what helps us grow - a do-or-die moment from which we emerge stronger and better.</p>
<p>I had a personal experience where I was completely isolated from my friends and family, forced to participate in activities that went against the core of my being, and lived in almost inhumane conditions. Was it a pleasant experience? Would I want something like that to happen to me again? Absolutely not. I experienced pain and suffering. But did I gain something from it? Definitely. I had a lot of time to reflect on my life, who I am, and what I believe in. Those harsh conditions stretched the limits of what I thought I could endure. I survived and returned stronger and more confident in myself, and for that, I am grateful. I chose to focus on the positive side of it all, rather than be consumed by sadness.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="can-there-be-too-much-of-a-good-thing">Can there Be Too much of a Good Thing?<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/why-im-an-optimist#can-there-be-too-much-of-a-good-thing" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Can there Be Too much of a Good Thing?" title="Direct link to Can there Be Too much of a Good Thing?">​</a></h2>
<p>Being too optimistic can be a bad thing. If we start seeing everything through rose-tinted glasses, we might miss out on some red flags. Thinking "there's good in every bad" might make us less risk-averse than we should be, causing us not to take the necessary precautions or to neglect developing our capabilities such that those negative things would be avoided in the first place. We become less inquisitive, less informed about potential hazards, and overconfident without the knowledge to back it up.</p>
<p>When optimism turns into wishful thinking or daydreaming without being balanced with a touch of realism, we might become careless about what happens to us, believing that "things will work out in the end," and forgetting the important distinction between what's within our power to change and our obligation to act on it.</p>
<p>So, why not just be a realist? Realists seem to have the best of both worlds: seeing the world "as it truly is" without judgment, trying to look only at the facts, and working with what they have. While it sounds promising, I think that being a realist is a false hope for two main reasons:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>We are never without our glasses</strong> - There is a long history of debate on whether we can ever truly remove our mental lenses through which we see the world - even down to perceiving simple details like shape or color. It's unclear if attempting to see the complex world of human interaction in its raw form, without Narratives or judgment, is worthwhile, let alone possible. Most likely, those who claim neutrality are more delusional than accurate.</li>
<li><strong>We are bad at prediction</strong> - Even if we could separate facts from opinions and look at the cold, hard reality, what does it tell us about the future? Unfortunately, humans are notoriously bad at making guesses, even educated ones. Political experts are mistaken more often than not, and even those who get it right are likely to fail on their next guess. Just look at how much data and complex math is required to create basic computer models to forecast the future - and even then, it's "approximately almost right." Therefore, just knowing the facts is not enough, since the future is still blurry. We are not exempt from making judgments that inherently involve values, beliefs, and biases.</li>
</ol>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="cultivating-balanced-optimism">Cultivating Balanced Optimism<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/why-im-an-optimist#cultivating-balanced-optimism" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Cultivating Balanced Optimism" title="Direct link to Cultivating Balanced Optimism">​</a></h2>
<p>It seems that to maintain a healthy level of optimism, we need to balance two extremes: "acknowledging the hardships of the world" and "noticing and reframing reality in a more positive, protective way."</p>
<p>So, how can we do both of these things?</p>
<p>How to Cultivate Realism:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Practice mindfulness</strong> - Try to quiet your mind and reflect on your thoughts, senses, and the world around you without any judgments or filters. Mindfulness helps you observe reality as it is, not as you wish it to be.</li>
<li><strong>Draw Your Circle of Control</strong> - Consider what you are capable of controlling in your life and what is beyond your control. For instance, you always have the freedom to choose how to react, how to use your spare time, and which commitments are still worth following. On the other hand, recognize that you don’t control the state of the economy, events of random luck, or how others choose to act.</li>
</ol>
<p>How to Cultivate Optimism:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Believe in Yourself</strong> - Embrace a growth mindset, trusting that you can change and grow. Avoid harsh self-criticism and practice self-compassion, recognizing that everyone makes mistakes and that they are opportunities for growth.</li>
<li><strong>Express gratitude</strong> - Reflect daily on what you are grateful for. These can be small things, such as enjoying a warm meal, having a pleasant conversation with a friend, or witnessing a beautiful sunrise.</li>
<li><strong>Be Kind</strong> - Make an effort to perform small acts of kindness each day. This could be as simple as holding the door for someone, helping a colleague at work, or doing something thoughtful for your partner or family.</li>
<li><strong>Reframe Challenges</strong> - Focus on how the challenges in your life can help you grow. Consider what you can learn from them, viewing them as opportunities to practice your skills, like a workout for the mind. Embrace them not just as a natural part of life, but as a necessary step to becoming a stronger, more resilient person.</li>
</ol>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/why-im-an-optimist#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2>
<p>Being an optimist is more than just seeing the glass as half full, it's about finding a tap and filling it completely. It's not about ignoring the half-empty side but rather taking action to address it, facing challenges head-on.</p>
<p>Being an optimist is a choice - one of the best choices we can make. It involves surrounding ourselves with positivity in the most protective way, believing in our power and the power of others to bring goodness into the world, while still acknowledging all the flaws and faults that exist. It means treating obstacles as opportunities for growth without dismissing the difficult emotions they bring.</p>
<p>Believing that everything and everyone is terrible is easy, but doing something to improve the situation is hard. It’s a struggle worth embracing, and it carries with it the awakening truth that optimism is the best and only solution for a better life. No matter how challenging it may be, it's better to be a hopeful optimist than a "right" pessimist.</p>]]></content>
        <category label="Mindset" term="Mindset"/>
        <category label="Motivation" term="Motivation"/>
        <category label="Perspective" term="Perspective"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Admitting Our Faults]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/Admitting-out-faults</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/Admitting-out-faults"/>
        <updated>2025-02-16T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[What if admitting you're wrong is the key to getting it right?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>What if admitting you're wrong is the key to getting it right?</strong><br>
<!-- -->We avoid facing our mistakes because it hurts, but denial only locks them in. This post explores why owning our flaws isn't weakness, but the first powerful step toward real growth and change.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="admitting_our_faults_post.webp" src="https://idanariav.com/assets/images/admitting_our_faults_post-5e509cddc4e426bec17eecf90a1b320d.webp" width="1221" height="850" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="admitting-mistakes-is-hard">Admitting Mistakes is Hard<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/Admitting-out-faults#admitting-mistakes-is-hard" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Admitting Mistakes is Hard" title="Direct link to Admitting Mistakes is Hard">​</a></h2>
<p>How hard is it to say "I'm wrong" or "I made a mistake"? Sometimes it feels that admitting our mistakes is even worse than the mistake itself.</p>
<p>Perhaps we have failed to notice that we made a mistake, or that we hope we can fix it before anyone else can see, but when we admit it we turn in into reality, it becomes common knowledge.</p>
<p>All of our faults, our imperfection and our "ugly sides" are now publicly displayed for everyone to see. It feels like an indication that we have failed as people, that not only our actions, but our identity is hurt, lacking, weak.</p>
<p>I was (and somewhat still am) afraid of admitting I'm wrong. Whenever I get criticized, I immediately go into defensive mode. I deny, I redirect, I rage, because I feel that to listen and agree is a proof of my low worth. Although, deep inside, I now that these reactions are strong precisely because the feedback is true, that I have failed, as if by denying it I can change reality.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-hidden-cost-of-denial">The Hidden Cost of Denial<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/Admitting-out-faults#the-hidden-cost-of-denial" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Hidden Cost of Denial" title="Direct link to The Hidden Cost of Denial">​</a></h2>
<p>While denying our mistakes makes us feel better on the short term, it's harmful in the long run.</p>
<p>We prioritize our Ego over our growth.</p>
<p>It means that instead of addressing these mistakes head on, we ignore them, which is a sure recipe of repeating them. It gets worse if on top of denying them we blame someone or something else, because this hurts not just our ability to deal with these specific mistakes, but also cultivates a mindset of helplessness, as if there was nothing you could have done differently, as if we are always right and perfect, and it is others who set us back.</p>
<p>Ironically, by ignoring our mistakes we turn them from momentary errors to a permanent stain on our identity. We hide them because we fear we are truly worthless, incompetent. We give them power over our lives, over our identity.</p>
<p>Removing their power is through taking ownership and accountability, by admitting them we show others that we are honest, that we can do better, that we wish to be better, that we don't let these moments define us, and that we take responsibility over our actions, our behavior, and not dismiss it or blame others when it's convenient.</p>
<p>Identifying with our mistakes is the best way to overcome them.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="actionable-tips-how-to-embrace-your-mistakes">Actionable Tips: How to Embrace Your Mistakes<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/Admitting-out-faults#actionable-tips-how-to-embrace-your-mistakes" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Actionable Tips: How to Embrace Your Mistakes" title="Direct link to Actionable Tips: How to Embrace Your Mistakes">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Pause &amp; Reflect</strong> – When faced with criticism, instead of reacting defensively, take a moment to listen. Recognize that they are trying to help you, that they criticize the action, not your identity.</li>
<li><strong>Reframe Failure</strong> – See mistakes as learning opportunities, not personal failures. Mistakes are valuable lessons, ones that we can learn only by examining them.</li>
<li><strong>Ask for Feedback</strong> – Don't run away from feedback, embrace it. Constant feedback has preventative qualities, providing insights that will reduce the number and the degree of our mistakes.</li>
<li><strong>Be future oriented</strong> – Analyze your mistakes in a forward looking way, focus on what you can do better next time.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-takeaway-the-power-of-owning-your-mistakes">The Takeaway: The Power of Owning Your Mistakes<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/Admitting-out-faults#the-takeaway-the-power-of-owning-your-mistakes" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Takeaway: The Power of Owning Your Mistakes" title="Direct link to The Takeaway: The Power of Owning Your Mistakes">​</a></h2>
<p>Saying "I was wrong" is a liberating experience. By taking ownership over our mistakes, we are able to overcome them. There is nothing to be ashamed of, it is a proof of character, rather than a stain on one, to admit that we were wrong.</p>
<p>As with failures in general, they are the stepping stones for our improvement, we try, we fail, we learn, to try to live without error is like trying to be the best painter in the world without ever holding a brush. Improving and failing are two sides of the same coin.</p>
<p>So be proud, that you had the courage to try, the courage to step out of your comfort zone, and the courage to own your mistakes.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="ask-yourself">Ask Yourself<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/Admitting-out-faults#ask-yourself" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Ask Yourself" title="Direct link to Ask Yourself">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>When was the last time I admitted I was wrong?</li>
<li>How do I feel about myself when I make a mistake?</li>
<li>How do I handle mistakes? Is there a learning process afterwards?</li>
</ul>]]></content>
        <category label="Accountability" term="Accountability"/>
        <category label="Challenges" term="Challenges"/>
        <category label="Change" term="Change"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Emotional Aikido - Turn Chaos into Momentum]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/chaos-into-momentum</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/chaos-into-momentum"/>
        <updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Do you ever feel like you're fighting with yourself?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Do you ever feel like you're fighting with yourself?</strong><br>
<!-- -->That inner conflict between your rational goals and emotional impulses might be holding you back more than you realize. In this post, we explore how bridging that internal divide can lead to clarity, energy, and real progress, without the burnout or guilt.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="emotional_aikido_post.webp" src="https://idanariav.com/assets/images/emotional_aikido_post-f50785b6522b15c5fa48daf8f16d0a58.webp" width="602" height="362" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="introduction">Introduction<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/chaos-into-momentum#introduction" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Introduction" title="Direct link to Introduction">​</a></h2>
<p>We have all faced struggles in our lives, especially internal ones. It's as if we are made up of two distinct selves: the "Rational " side that strives for action without excuses, and the "emotional" side that prefers the easier, more enjoyable path.</p>
<p>While we strongly feel these two separates sides and how often they clash, by viewing ourselves this way we are setting ourselves up for failure. This false dichotomy often leads us to ruin, whether through apathy, self-hatred, or losing track of what matters most. When we leave ourselves divided, we fail to benefit from the energy and determination of a unified whole, like trying to use bikes without handles, or alternatively a bike with no wheels. We need both to prosper.</p>
<p>Today we'll discuss how to do just that, and I hope you've got your sweatshirts and headbands ready because I like to call this method <em>Emotional Aikido</em>. But first let's explain why each side is insufficient on its own, and how can we bring these two parts together.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="why-cant-i-just-power-through">Why Can't I just "power through"<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/chaos-into-momentum#why-cant-i-just-power-through" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why Can't I just &quot;power through&quot;" title="Direct link to Why Can't I just &quot;power through&quot;">​</a></h2>
<p><em>"Tomorrow I'll do better."</em> Famous first, and often last, words of many commitments. Unfortunately, most end up repeating the same negative routines. It could be going to the gym, starting that healthy diet, or calling friends and family. More often than not, these promises go unfulfilled.</p>
<p>In modern times, perhaps since the great scientific revolution and the Enlightenment, we've placed too much trust in our brains. We believe that "if there is a will, there is a way," only to end up on the same path as before. What we need to understand is that Willpower is Limited, and relying solely on "powering through" to achieve our goals is not only ineffective or delusional but can also be harmful.</p>
<p>We tend to believe that willpower works like this:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Motivation</strong> - We start with motivation, perhaps sparked by a strong desire to change something in our lives.</li>
<li><strong>Action</strong> - We begin to take action, aligning with our goals, and we feel as if it will be smooth sailing from now on.</li>
<li><strong>Change</strong> - We start seeing changes resulting from these actions and embrace them wholeheartedly.</li>
</ol>
<p>However, this model is misleading, and our life experiences may have already shown us that it's not as simple as it seems.</p>
<p>A more accurate representation of reality involves understanding that change is not always a guaranteed outcome when relying on rationality alone. Moreover, there are two infinite loops we can easily get trapped in if we aren't careful: the loops of apathy and Procrastination. I call them the "why even try" and "why not tomorrow" cycles. Once we enter these loops, they can be incredibly difficult to escape.</p>
<p>Therefore, the first step is to understand what causes us to fall into these loops in the first place.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="why-even-try">Why even Try?<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/chaos-into-momentum#why-even-try" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why even Try?" title="Direct link to Why even Try?">​</a></h3>
<p>We often end up discouraged after a failure, which is almost inevitable. Maybe you accidentally skip a workout, the healthy diet isn't showing results, or you've had a rough day and just can't muster the strength to follow through. When these setbacks happen once or twice, we might be able to push through and reignite our motivation to start again. However, each failure can feel like a tiny puncture in a wheel; eventually, there's no air left to keep going. Instead of starting again, we simply give up. The world starts to look like a pessimistic and deterministic place, where failure seems predestined, so there's no point in even trying.</p>
<p>Escaping this cycle is challenging because it requires us to "forget" the lessons we've learned the hard way and take a leap and try again. Even when every fiber of our being tells us it's foolish to attempt something that can only lead to disappointment.</p>
<p>Whether fueled by anger at the world, anger at ourselves, or both, falling into this pit of despair makes it incredibly difficult to climb back out.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="why-not-tomorrow">Why not Tomorrow<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/chaos-into-momentum#why-not-tomorrow" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why not Tomorrow" title="Direct link to Why not Tomorrow">​</a></h3>
<p>A second infinite cycle, perhaps more elusive than the first, is the cycle of procrastination, the "why not tomorrow" loop. After all, you can't fail if you never try. Unlike the first cycle, it’s not that we lack motivation, we might even be genuinely optimistic about how our lives could improve when we will start to act differently. The problem is that "now is not the right time."</p>
<p>The fear of Failure pushes us to set the bar so high for what we consider success that it becomes nearly unattainable. For example, what's the point of working out for just 20 minutes a week if a "good" workout must last at least 45 minutes? And since I don't have that much time right now, it's better not to do it at all. Or perhaps, we think that we are not yet worthy, for example who am I to write a blog post about productivity? I should read and study more until I'm absolutely certain I'm an expert on the topic. Until then, I won’t write a single word!</p>
<p>If in the previous example, each failure was like a puncture in our tires, then here, we won't even start the car unless we have complete information about the road conditions, the state of the car, and are 100% certain we’ll reach our destination.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="why-cant-i-just-do-it-when-i-feel-like-it">Why Can't I just Do it when I Feel like it<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/chaos-into-momentum#why-cant-i-just-do-it-when-i-feel-like-it" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why Can't I just Do it when I Feel like it" title="Direct link to Why Can't I just Do it when I Feel like it">​</a></h2>
<p>Just like with the rational side, there’s also the emotional side. Whether due to personal tastes, beliefs, or disappointment with rational approaches, we may shift to a mindset that relies on our internal world of emotions and sensations as the source of our actions, rather than cold, rational decision-making.</p>
<p>For instance, we might believe that life is like a flowing river that shouldn’t be controlled. Perhaps we realize that our disappointment with the rational approach stems from something within us resisting the change, so we decide to listen to our feelings, to our body, and do what feels right.</p>
<p>This might sound similar to the "why not tomorrow" case, but the difference is that in that scenario, the desire was for complete control and knowledge before taking action. Here, it’s not about control but rather motivation. The driver isn’t concerned with the car or the road, they are simply not sure if they want to drive at all. Unlike the "why even try" scenario, it’s not that we believe it’s doomed from the start, we might even think that if we truly wanted to, we could succeed, we’re just not sure if we want to, or prefer to leave things to nature, fate or chance instead of being the driver ourselves.</p>
<p>So, what’s wrong with this approach? Relying solely on internal feelings can lead to:</p>
<ol start="4">
<li><strong>Inconsistency</strong> - Even with habits that feel most natural to us, we don’t always find the Intrinsic Motivation to stick with them. If we only act when we feel like it, our actions are likely to be inconsistent, which won't help us achieve our goals. For example, working out once a month is unlikely to yield the desired results.</li>
<li><strong>Imbalance</strong> - On the other hand, we can sometimes get so caught up in what we're doing that we forget everything else. This sense of Flow is often a good thing, but without knowing when to stop, it can lead to extreme outcomes, such as becoming a workaholic or developing a "one-track mind."</li>
<li><strong>Misalignment</strong> - Not everything that feels good is necessarily good for us. Unfortunately, nearly everything, from food to mass media, has been engineered to affect us emotionally. If we use our biological tendencies as guides, we can sometimes be led astray by our emotions.</li>
</ol>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-solution-emotional-aikido">The Solution? Emotional Aikido<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/chaos-into-momentum#the-solution-emotional-aikido" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Solution? Emotional Aikido" title="Direct link to The Solution? Emotional Aikido">​</a></h2>
<p>This is just one tool in our overarching plan to achieve balance. The main idea is simple: instead of fighting against yourself, work with yourself to achieve better results.</p>
<p>But why call it "emotional aikido"? Aikido is a Japanese martial art often translated as "the path of harmony," where you act to preserve not only yourself but also your opponent, discouraging violence and aggression. The way to achieve this is by using your opponent's momentum against them.</p>
<p>An easy example: if an opponent is running at you, you can either stand your ground and fight, or step aside and trip them. In doing so, you use all their energy and momentum against them, turning their attack into their downfall.</p>
<p>So how does this apply to our topic? The answer is perhaps simple to understand yet harder to implement: as with most things, the answer lies in the middle. Yes, we need to listen to our body and emotions when we act. Trying to "push through" and force ourselves to do something we don’t truly want is a waste of time. However, acting solely based on feelings lacks the structure, direction, and consistency provided by a rational approach.</p>
<p>So, how do we connect these two parts?</p>
<ol start="7">
<li><strong>Know Thyself</strong> - Regularly perform self-checks, asking yourself how you feel in the moment and noticing patterns that arise. For instance, maybe you avoid working out because you're ashamed of how you look, or your motivation for writing comes from a desire to support others and help them learn from your mistakes.</li>
<li><strong>Plan with the Heart in Mind</strong> - Now that we know what makes us tick, we can find ways to motivate ourselves without relying on sheer willpower. Techniques like Temptation Bundling, priming your environment, and motivational scheduling are just a few examples. If we plan this way, we may slowly see ourselves beginning to enjoy doing what is good, and those hard actions suddenly become easier.</li>
<li><strong>Convert Failure to Fuel</strong> - A common saying in Stoicism is that good or bad is a result of internal judgment, independent of external events. While this may not apply to every situation, we can certainly adopt this mindset regarding failure. By seeing failures as opportunities to learn and grow rather than as a mark of shame, we can completely shift our motivation. Failure means you’re not there yet, not that you can't get there. Sometimes, failure contains the lessons needed to ensure we don’t repeat it and achieve Mastery, provided we spend enough time listening to it. We are not defined by our failures, but by how we respond to them.</li>
</ol>
<p>If instead of fighting ourselves, we listen,
if instead of making it hard, we make it easy,
if instead of getting angry, we get excited,
then we have mastered emotional aikido.</p>
<p>Our emotions, even the "bad ones" and perhaps especially the bad ones, such as jealously, envy, anger and frustration are the greatest source of fuel we have. Rather than being denied or ignored, they should be embraced. They are like a storm brewing with us, waiting for something to strike. It is the rational side's job to funnel that immense energy to a positive outlet, to ride that storm until we reach our destination. Fuel and direction, emotion and rationality, we need them both.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/chaos-into-momentum#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2>
<p>We've explored two models of thinking-to-action: one based on rationality and the other on emotionality. Each, when used in isolation, has its pitfalls:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Rationality without emotions</strong> leads to burnout, self-hatred, and procrastination.</li>
<li><strong>Emotions without rationality</strong> result in inconsistency, misalignment, and imbalance.</li>
</ul>
<p>But when combined, these two approaches create a powerful synergy that is greater than the sum of its parts. The rational side offers direction and structure, while the emotional side provides the fuel. By merging them, you can work smart, not hard. And as a bonus, this blend not only enhances productivity but also fosters balance and well-being in life. 😊</p>
<h1>Further Reading:</h1>
<p>Ego Is The Enemy (book)
The Obstacle Is the Way (book)
Mindset (book)
Flow (book)</p>]]></content>
        <category label="Motivation" term="Motivation"/>
        <category label="Emotions" term="Emotions"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Say Yes To Less]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/say-yes-to-less</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/say-yes-to-less"/>
        <updated>2025-01-19T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Feeling overwhelmed and falling short on all fronts?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Feeling overwhelmed and falling short on all fronts?</strong><br>
<!-- -->When everything feels urgent, nothing truly moves forward. This post dives into why doing less strategically can help you do more of what really matters. Let go of guilt, cut the noise, and focus your energy where it counts.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="overwhelm-and-overcommitment">Overwhelm and Overcommitment<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/say-yes-to-less#overwhelm-and-overcommitment" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Overwhelm and Overcommitment" title="Direct link to Overwhelm and Overcommitment">​</a></h3>
<p>What are you planning to do after reading this? Perhaps you need to work, get groceries, handle some bureaucracy, help a friend, pursue personal goals, fix that thing that’s been broken for weeks, or maybe even all of the above. Especially now when a new year has just started and promises of "new year new me" have been pilling up, it’s no wonder we often feel overwhelmed, like there just aren’t enough hours in the day. Even if the days were twice as long, it might still not feel like enough to clear our endless to-do lists.</p>
<p>The commitments we juggle - to ourselves, to friends, to our partners, and to the lifestyles we aspire to create - can easily become overwhelming. This constant pressure leaves us frustrated or, worse, guilty for failing to meet our own expectations and those of others. The feeling of not doing enough, of not being enough, becomes an ever-present shadow.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="do-less-to-achieve-more">Do Less to Achieve More<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/say-yes-to-less#do-less-to-achieve-more" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Do Less to Achieve More" title="Direct link to Do Less to Achieve More">​</a></h3>
<p>The truth is simple and unavoidable: there will never be enough time. As long as we fail to set boundaries and say no, we’ll remain trapped in the cycle of trying to do it all. And while doing it all might sound admirable, in reality, “all” includes both the significant and the trivial. Our time is limited, we must learn to be selective.</p>
<p>Saying no is about more than refusing requests - it’s about choosing what to focus on. Saying yes to less allows us to devote our energy to what truly matters, making meaningful progress on priorities instead of getting stuck in the endless churn of busyness. By doing less, we can ultimately achieve more.</p>
<p>Saying no is hard, especially to ourselves. Our dreams are endless and our time so limited, but this is precisely why we need to narrow down, to prioritize what we spend time on, and have the strength to say no to the trivial. When you know what's important to you and why, it's easier to say no to the rest.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="actionable-tips-to-simplify-and-prioritize">Actionable Tips to Simplify and Prioritize<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/say-yes-to-less#actionable-tips-to-simplify-and-prioritize" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Actionable Tips to Simplify and Prioritize" title="Direct link to Actionable Tips to Simplify and Prioritize">​</a></h3>
<ol>
<li><strong>Audit your commitments:</strong>
<ol>
<li>Make a list of everything currently on your plate. Identify which commitments align with your core values and goals.</li>
<li>Highlight tasks that can be postponed, delegated, or removed entirely.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li><strong>Set boundaries:</strong>
<ol>
<li>Practice saying "no" to new commitments that don’t align with your priorities.</li>
<li>Communicate openly with others about adjusting expectations to manage your workload realistically.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li><strong>Focus deeply:</strong>
<ol>
<li>Choose one or two high-priority tasks to focus on each day. Channel your energy into these instead of spreading yourself thin.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li><strong>Let go of guilt:</strong>
<ol>
<li>Remind yourself that doing less is not failure - it’s a strategic choice to dedicate your best efforts to what truly matters.</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-takeaway">The Takeaway<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/say-yes-to-less#the-takeaway" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Takeaway" title="Direct link to The Takeaway">​</a></h3>
<p>Feeling overwhelmed isn’t a sign of weakness - it’s a signal to reassess and refocus. By doing less, you can free yourself from guilt, make meaningful progress, and give your best to the commitments that matter most.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="ask-yourself">Ask yourself<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/say-yes-to-less#ask-yourself" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Ask yourself" title="Direct link to Ask yourself">​</a></h3>
<ol>
<li>Imagine your life from scratch, commitment free. How would you feel? How will it be different?</li>
<li>Now when the slate is clean. Which commitments on your plate are the most meaningful to you?</li>
<li>What’s one promise or task you can let go of?</li>
<li>What’s one area of your life where you could set clearer boundaries to protect your time and energy?</li>
</ol>]]></content>
        <category label="Focus" term="Focus"/>
        <category label="Minimalism" term="Minimalism"/>
        <category label="Reflection" term="Reflection"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to remember who we are]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/how-to-remember-who-we-are</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/how-to-remember-who-we-are"/>
        <updated>2025-01-03T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ever feel like you're losing sight of who you are?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Ever feel like you're losing sight of who you are?</strong><br>
<!-- -->As time passes, even our values and sense of identity can fade into the background. Journaling helps us stay grounded, connecting past, present, and future into a clear, cohesive story. Here's why making it a habit can save you from future identity crises.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="confused-so-am-i">Confused? So am I<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/how-to-remember-who-we-are#confused-so-am-i" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Confused? So am I" title="Direct link to Confused? So am I">​</a></h2>
<p>Have you ever found yourself suddenly "awake", as if you have been on autopilot, not sure what just happened? This "awakening" can be as little as "how did I get here" moments or "what was I just doing" and as large as an existential crisis such as "what I am doing with my life".</p>
<p>We humans are naturally curious; we tend to seek causality, even when it isn't really there. These questions pop up once in a while from our subconscious, reminding us that there are some unresolved thoughts or feelings, some voice inside us that tries to bring us back on track. The "bigger" the question, the harder it is to resolve.</p>
<p>Life, especially on autopilot, is like playing a game of "musical chairs in a kitchen". Imagine a group of people, where each person has only 15 minutes to cook something before they have to switch with someone else, leaving no instructions or clues. You could imagine our quickly it can turn into a disaster. In life, it is if every moment a new "us" enters the picture, trying to make sense of what has happened before, and what can we do now. These moments are confusion are exactly when we have failed to put the pieces of our lives together, that we can't connect anymore to our unifying narrative, if we even have one. In our cooking example, we might choose to start over, throwing away past investments to the trash, or going with the flow and creating something edible at best.</p>
<p>Imagine the same scenario, but this time all the cooks had a shared recipe, and they could leave a note to each other before they switch. Instead of a mess in the kitchen, we would probably get a decent meal.</p>
<p>The same can be done in our personal lives. We often expect too much of ourselves, that we would be able to remember everything in our minds, despite quickly losing focus and forgetting, even things as important as our identity, our values, our goals and what brings us meaning in life.</p>
<p>We are not a goldfish, but not a computer either, and even these can be overloaded and crash. To prevent this crisis from happen we need to offload, to have a record of our thoughts, our identity, to help us remember the most important things exactly when we need to. While offloading may sound like we let something external take control of us, it's exactly the opposite. It will be our words, our thoughts, our time capsules of identities that will echo back to us.</p>
<p>Journaling is a simple yet profound solution, with three main advantages:</p>
<ol>
<li>Remembering the past</li>
<li>Understanding the present</li>
<li>Planning for the future</li>
</ol>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="remembering-the-past">Remembering the past<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/how-to-remember-who-we-are#remembering-the-past" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Remembering the past" title="Direct link to Remembering the past">​</a></h2>
<p>We now live in a world where we have to navigate the constant, endless sea of content on own own, while everyone else is vying for our  attention (or our wallet's) for as much as possible.</p>
<p>In this Pavlovian world of notifications, it’s no wonder that we can only concentrate for a few minutes before feeling the urge to switch to something else. This often leads to three unfortunate outcomes:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>The important is forgotten</strong> - We tend to forget things a lot. It could be birthdays, tasks that need to be completed, or, most importantly, our most valuable moments. Time spent with friends and family, unique experiences, or even just enjoying the little things in life. Whether because we aren't fully present physically or mentally, those moments tend to drift away if we don't pay attention.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Change is unnoticeable</strong> - Without a clear record of our mental state at different times, we might assume that we've always believed what we believe today, that we share values, thoughts, and feelings with our past selves. Habits deeply entrenched in our minds feel as if they have always been there. The present is hard enough to process through our current lens, so imagining what our past self would have thought is practically impossible.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Value requires reflection</strong> - We don't always appreciate what we have or experience the first time around. Sometimes it takes years for the importance to sink in and change us forever. If the message is lost before we reach that stage, we will never be able to benefit from this understanding.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="understanding-the-present">Understanding the Present<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/how-to-remember-who-we-are#understanding-the-present" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Understanding the Present" title="Direct link to Understanding the Present">​</a></h2>
<p>When we are bombarded with so much information vying for our attention, it is not surprising if we fail to notice the more subtle cues that hide in plain sight, since not everything worth saying is necessarily being told.</p>
<p>There's a famous story about a policeman who sees a drunk man searching for something under a streetlight and asks what he has lost. The man says he lost his keys, and they both search under the streetlight together. After a few minutes, the policeman asks if he is sure he lost them there, and the drunk replies no, that he lost them in the park. When the policeman asks why he's searching under the streetlight, the drunk replies, "this is where the light is."</p>
<p>If we focus only on what we "see," we will likely miss the important things that are a bit harder to perceive. For example, we can't see into the minds of others. Sometimes we are not necessarily aware of our own thoughts, so how could we know what others are thinking? Instead of asking others to be more transparent, we default to making false assumptions. And you know what they say about those who assume... To make things worse, we also have the tendency to assume the worst.
If someone does something wrong, we assume it was intentional, if they fail to do something good, we assume it's because they don't care.</p>
<p>Another common false assumption is thinking that others see the world the same way we do, whether it’s due to shared information, beliefs, or values. A well known experiment tests children by placing them in a room with an adult who hides an object in Box A. The adult then leaves the room, and the experimenter moves the object from Box A to Box B. The child is asked where the adult will search for the object when they return. Those who answer B do not realize their knowledge is not "automatically" shared with everyone.</p>
<p>It might seem easy to outsmart this (after all, it’s a children’s test), but adults fail too. For example, I might expect something from my partner simply because "I thought I told you about it," or because "I thought you knew me well enough that it goes without saying." These cases often end in arguments caused by miscommunication that could have been easily resolved.</p>
<p>Lastly, it might not be others we are failing to understand, but the situation as a whole. We often lack Context, which usually requires remembering what has happened before and why (do you remember the previous chapter?). Focusing only on what's in front of us without context could cause us to miss the meaning of what we're doing. For example, going to the gym without remembering how you felt afterward or the sense of satisfaction when you weigh yourself each weekend could easily make you lose interest in going again. Similarly, small incremental changes might be too minor to notice daily, but looking back over a month or a year can make them much more noticeable. For example, reading just 10 pages a day sounds insignificant, but it adds up to a book a month, which is actually quite a lot.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="preparing-for-the-future">Preparing for the Future<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/how-to-remember-who-we-are#preparing-for-the-future" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Preparing for the Future" title="Direct link to Preparing for the Future">​</a></h2>
<p>A famous quote says, "Those who don't learn from history are bound to repeat it." While not all learning is writing (although some might argue otherwise), writing things down significantly increases the likelihood that we will remember them. By documenting our thoughts - what we did well, what went wrong, we're much more likely to internalize those lessons and act differently in the future.</p>
<p>Building on this, writing can help us detect patterns. When we develop a habit of writing regularly, we are more likely to notice recurring behaviors over time. As imperfect humans, we might make the same mistake twice or even a third time. In such cases, writing can help us identify these patterns, provide a stable source of learning, and serve as a foundation for possible solutions. For example, if we jot down all the instances where we failed to stick to our routines, it might prompt us to think about why that is. Perhaps it's because a part of us resists it, or maybe we just need to plan better to align with our motivation.</p>
<p>However, merely writing without reviewing what we've written is similar to hoping we can remember everything without any aid - but that’s a topic for another post.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="so-how-do-we-start">So how do we start?<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/how-to-remember-who-we-are#so-how-do-we-start" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to So how do we start?" title="Direct link to So how do we start?">​</a></h2>
<p>The good thing about journaling is that it's personal. You decide when and how to write, and about what. Journaling is a practice that helps even if we never read again what we've written. The act itself of writing reengages us with our thoughts, turning the mess in our mind into a clear narrative.</p>
<p>You could start with morning pages, where you write as soon as you wake up 1-3 pages of whatever you like. You can try bullet journaling, daily reviews, weekly reviews, carrying a small notepad and writing thoughts as they come up. Try, try different methods and see what resonates with you, and see what helps you remember the past, understanding the present, and planning for the future.</p>
<p>It might be weird at first, staring at a blank page and starting a written conversation with... yourself? But you never know, you might like it, and someday, it might even get published:)</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="further-reading">Further Reading<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/how-to-remember-who-we-are#further-reading" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Further Reading" title="Direct link to Further Reading">​</a></h2>
<p>It wasn't the main message of any one book, but some books reference it
How to think like a roman emperor (book)
First Things First (book)
The 12 week year (book)</p>]]></content>
        <category label="Writing" term="Writing"/>
        <category label="Personal-Identity" term="Personal-Identity"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Taking Control of Your Attention]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/taking-control-of-your-attention</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/taking-control-of-your-attention"/>
        <updated>2024-12-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Are you living intentionally—=, or just reacting to the noise around you?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Are you living intentionally—=, or just reacting to the noise around you?</strong><br>
<!-- -->In a world full of distractions, it's easy to slip into autopilot. But real change starts when we pause, reflect, and choose our path with clarity. Here's how to reclaim your focus and take back control.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-rarest-commodity-undivided-attention">The rarest commodity: undivided attention<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/taking-control-of-your-attention#the-rarest-commodity-undivided-attention" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The rarest commodity: undivided attention" title="Direct link to The rarest commodity: undivided attention">​</a></h3>
<p>When was the last time you were fully immersed in a single task, completely "in the zone"? If this happens often for you, you’re among a rare group, and the rest of us could certainly use your advice! Reaching this state of flow is incredibly challenging, especially when our minds are perpetually crowded with countless tasks waiting to be addressed.</p>
<p>The sheer volume of these tasks is daunting enough, but their source matters, too. It’s one thing to generate your own to-do list; it’s another to be inundated by the expectations and priorities of others. From well-meaning colleagues seeking help to the relentless pull of social media and advertising, Distractions clamor for our attention, often steering us away from what truly matters. This fractured focus drain our energy and leaves us mentally scattered. No wonder we often emerge from doom-scrolling or task-switching feeling exhausted and unfulfilled.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="pause-reflect-act">Pause, Reflect, Act<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/taking-control-of-your-attention#pause-reflect-act" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Pause, Reflect, Act" title="Direct link to Pause, Reflect, Act">​</a></h3>
<p>Our minds are designed to thrive on deep focus, yet modern life constantly pulls us in multiple directions. Breaking free from this cycle requires more than willpower; it demands a deliberate reset.</p>
<p>The first step is to Pause. Like the old "stop, drop, and roll" advice for emergencies, breaking out of autopilot begins by stopping in our tracks. This moment of stillness interrupts the cycle of distraction, giving us a chance to regain control before we’re swept away by the next default behavior.</p>
<p>Pausing creates space for Reflection. In this brief interval, we can assess the situation with fresh perspective, untangling ourselves from the emotions and impulses that led us astray. This clarity allows us to choose a better course of action—one aligned with our true priorities.</p>
<p>Finally, with renewed focus and energy, we can act intentionally. By directing our undivided attention to the one task or goal that matters most in the moment, we reclaim the power to engage deeply with our lives. The rare gift of full attention is not only a commodity worth striving for but also a foundation for meaningful work and personal fulfillment.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="actionable-tips-to-regain-control">Actionable Tips to Regain Control<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/taking-control-of-your-attention#actionable-tips-to-regain-control" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Actionable Tips to Regain Control" title="Direct link to Actionable Tips to Regain Control">​</a></h3>
<ol>
<li><strong>Pause:</strong> Set aside just 5–10 minutes a day to step away from distractions. Use this time for calm reflection.</li>
<li><strong>Reflect:</strong> Ask yourself: <em>What’s currently demanding my attention? Is it truly worth it?</em></li>
<li><strong>Prioritize:</strong> Identify one thing that aligns with your goals or values to focus on.</li>
<li><strong>Take Action:</strong> Commit to a small, meaningful step toward what matters most to you.</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-takeaway">The Takeaway<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/taking-control-of-your-attention#the-takeaway" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Takeaway" title="Direct link to The Takeaway">​</a></h3>
<p>By regularly pausing and reflecting, we can reclaim our attention, make clearer decisions, and focus on what truly matters—living a life of intentionality rather than default.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="ask-yourself">Ask yourself<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/taking-control-of-your-attention#ask-yourself" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Ask yourself" title="Direct link to Ask yourself">​</a></h3>
<ol>
<li>What are the biggest sources of noise in your life right now?</li>
<li>When was the last time you paused to assess where your attention and energy are going?</li>
<li>What’s one default behavior or routine you’ve fallen into that you’d like to change?</li>
<li>How would your life feel different if you focused only on what truly matters to you?</li>
</ol>]]></content>
        <category label="Focus" term="Focus"/>
        <category label="Reflection" term="Reflection"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Turn pain into growth]]></title>
        <id>https://idanariav.com/blog/turn-pain-into-growth</id>
        <link href="https://idanariav.com/blog/turn-pain-into-growth"/>
        <updated>2024-12-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[What if the very struggles you try to avoid are the ones that hold the key to your growth?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>What if the very struggles you try to avoid are the ones that hold the key to your growth?</strong><br>
<!-- -->Could reframing pain as a path, not a problem, be the mindset shift that helps you thrive—not just survive—through life’s challenges?</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="avoiding-challenges">Avoiding Challenges<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/turn-pain-into-growth#avoiding-challenges" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Avoiding Challenges" title="Direct link to Avoiding Challenges">​</a></h3>
<p>Nobody actively seeks Hardships. We crave a peaceful, enjoyable life where we can focus on what we love and spend time with those who matter. Hardships, with their struggles, exhaustion, and pain, seem like the antithesis of happiness—roadblocks we’d rather avoid altogether. And when obstacles feel insurmountable, the stakes grow even higher. Failure can challenge not only our skills but also our self-image, shaking our confidence and how we think others perceive us. Avoiding challenges might seem like the safer, better option.</p>
<p>But a life devoid of challenges feels oddly hollow, like playing a game with cheat codes. It is precisely when we push ourselves to the limits of our abilities, testing our resolve, that we feel fully engaged and alive. A smooth, obstacle-free life might keep us comfortable, but it offers little in the way of growth or fulfillment. Without challenges, we abandon the very paths that lead to our personal and professional development.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="embracing-obstacles">Embracing Obstacles<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/turn-pain-into-growth#embracing-obstacles" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Embracing Obstacles" title="Direct link to Embracing Obstacles">​</a></h3>
<p>Growth, however, rarely comes without effort. embracing obstacles isn’t about making them easy but about reshaping how we perceive them. Obstacles, by their nature, test our character and skills. Learning to view them as opportunities rather than misfortunes can fundamentally shift our approach to life. This perspective is itself a challenge, but one that pays immense dividends.</p>
<p>When we stop seeing hardships as enemies to our happiness and instead accept them as opportunities to grow, we begin to change the story we tell ourselves. Obstacles stop being threats to avoid and become milestones to overcome. They become less about ego and more about progress, transforming helplessness into proactiveness and pessimism into optimism. By reframing our perspective, we can move through life with greater clarity, confidence, and resilience, viewing each challenge as an invitation to become better.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="actionable-tips-to-embracing-challenges">Actionable Tips to Embracing Challenges<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/turn-pain-into-growth#actionable-tips-to-embracing-challenges" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Actionable Tips to Embracing Challenges" title="Direct link to Actionable Tips to Embracing Challenges">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Shift Your Perspective:</strong>
<ul>
<li>When faced with a difficulty, ask yourself: <em>What can I learn from this? How can this make me stronger?</em></li>
<li>Reframe challenges as stepping stones rather than roadblocks.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Take Small Steps:</strong>
<ul>
<li>Break down the obstacle into manageable actions. Progress, even if small, builds momentum.</li>
<li>Celebrate each step forward to maintain motivation.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Stay Resilient:</strong>
<ul>
<li>Accept that discomfort is part of growth. Remind yourself that the effort will pay off.</li>
<li>Lean on tools like journaling or supportive conversations to process struggles constructively.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Make It Fun:</strong>
<ul>
<li>Find joy in the process. Approach challenges with curiosity, treating them as puzzles to solve rather than burdens to bear.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-takeaway">The Takeaway<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/turn-pain-into-growth#the-takeaway" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Takeaway" title="Direct link to The Takeaway">​</a></h3>
<p>Obstacles are not the enemy—they are the pathway to growth. By recognizing the opportunities hidden within challenges and facing them head-on, we become stronger, wiser, and better equipped to handle life’s complexities.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="ask-yourself">Ask yourself<a href="https://idanariav.com/blog/turn-pain-into-growth#ask-yourself" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Ask yourself" title="Direct link to Ask yourself">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>How do you usually respond to challenges—do you face them or avoid them?</li>
<li>Can you recall a past obstacle that helped you grow in unexpected ways?</li>
<li>What’s one current difficulty you could reframe as an opportunity for growth?</li>
<li>What small, actionable step can you take today to move closer to overcoming it?</li>
</ul>]]></content>
        <category label="Challenges" term="Challenges"/>
        <category label="Motivation" term="Motivation"/>
    </entry>
</feed>